<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>George Rice and the First International Polar Year Expedition</title>
<link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/</link>
<atom:link href="https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.5</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 21:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>1882-04-06:1882-04-10</title>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-04-06/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="thursday-april-6th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-april-6th-1882">Thursday April 6th, 1882</h2>
<p>When we reached Lincoln Bay it was 6 a.m. We had made the distance, including stop at Wrangle Bay in 15 hours. The Dr.&nbsp;set to work to prepare us a meal and Jens and I turned in. Meanwhile, the former had his own experience to relate, Left without a watch he used the bold point of Cape Frederick VII for a sundial and was able to inform us of the day and almost the hour. The dogs kept him company and we found “Redeye” installed in the corner of the igloo with one little puppy. It appears that both “Redeye” and Milatook added to the canine population of Grinnell Land, but of both families all but one little chubby spotted fellow disappeared down the capricious jaws of their fathers. The survivor then became a bone of contention to the bereaved mothers and our son of Galen did not know to which it should be awarded. Under the impression that “Redeye” had lost the greatest number he decided in her favor. It is unnecessary to state that the Dr.&nbsp;understood the allusion when he is addressed as Solomon — Poor Red did not enjoy the maternal office long for Kingatook (to use Jens term) “scoffed” the tender scion of caninity.</p>
<p>At 7 p.m. we again abandoned our snowhouse and started north. For several succeeding days (see sledge diary) we were engaged in hauling our stores from Cape Union to Black Cape. The traveling was very difficult; the icefoot inclining at a sharp angle from the cliffs to the sea and presenting an inclined plane along which the dogs crawled—the sledge following on only one runner most of the time and always in imminent danger of toppling over. The surface of the road was glazed by the sun and so slippery that at times the whole caravan—dogs, sledge and men—would slide swiftly from the foot of the cliffs to the line of paleocrystic bergs below, among which we floundered. At other times the faithful dogs would succeed in maintaining their hold by inserting their sharp claws in the crust but the sledge and we with it would describe the section of a circle with the dogs for a center and their traces as a radii. When the pressed up ice in the foot disrupted our passage we would take to the Straits but the traveling there was as if and immense inverted harrow. Our watch stopped on the 7th and set by guess. On the 8th and 9th it blew a gale part of the time, on the latter day when at Black Cape compelling us to take down tent and build snowhouse. Temperature warmer (see sledge diary).</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-april-10th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-april-10th-1882">Monday April 10th 1882</h2>
<p>At Black Cape. Wind blew so hard that a little after midnight the tent was blown from its ropes and we had to fold it up at 4 am. It abated a little and encouraged us to start although still strong enough to almost take us off our feet. At 5 a.m. we were over the icefront on the Straits -Temp 0. Wind began to increase. In smooth places propelling the sledge in an alarming manner (wind was in our backs) and crowding on the poor dogs who were leaving the marks of their nails on the ice in their desperate effort to keep from being blown away. One of us and the driver would support himself by the upstands of the sledge and the other was frequently seen to throw himself prone upon the ice to prevent being dashed along and hurled against the blocks of ice.</p>
<p>At 10 a.m. we reached Cape Rauson near Alert’s winter q’rt’s and found we could proceed no further as the gale was increasing and the dogs could not be managed. The icefoot here placed us 50 ft above the sea level, and we could not trust ourselves in the high icy pinnacles without fear of being blown off. Wrapping our sleeping bags under the lee of a hummock we crawled in, munching some hard bread to satisfy our hunger. The dogs curled themselves up for a nap, and here we remained all through the day and the night, the snow drifting in the sleeping bags about our faces despite all our precautions with the flaps, so great was the force of the searching wind even in a sheltered place. At times during the night we would get up for observations and to relieve our bodies from the cramped positions in the sleeping bags but at no time was it possible to make a start. It was almost impossible to stand upright and locomotion was out of the question without holding onto ice and rocks. At this place, Cape Rauson, we found a can of pemmican left by the English. It was indicated by a small cairn of rocks which first attracted our attention. Cairn contained 32 lbs and we found it excellent eating even without cooking. In my sledge journal of this date I find I have complimented the fortitude and patience of our faithful team of dogs. Even now I can think of nothing connected with our trip that so stirs my breast with kindly emotion as the remembrance of fine animals struggling day after day through ice and snow, piercing winds and blinding drifts, dragging heavy loads over rough rugged roads with their feet sometimes cut and bleeding from the icy chrystals.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-04-06/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1882-04-02:1882-04-02</title>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-04-02/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="sunday-april-2nd-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-april-2nd-1882">Sunday April 2nd 1882</h2>
<p>On our way back to snowhouse after our accident last night I told the Dr.&nbsp;that I could make the trip to home station, Fort Conger, and return on foot in five days and offered to go. It was the only way out of our difficulty that suggested itself. I thought a sledge runner could be made for us at short notice and the loss of time, although considerable, was not so great as to necessarily frustrate our plans for the trip. To give up after spending so much time and effort would have been a great disappointment. I sympathized most sincerely with the Dr.&nbsp;to whom the misfortune was greater than to myself. Dr.&nbsp;Pavy was at first quite averse to my project as it appears to him rather too hazardous. After discussing the matter for some time I overcame his objections and desired to start at once—but I will here copy my report which I submitted for his information when making up his arrival report to the commanding officer after our return.</p>
<p>In accordance with your request I hereby submit a short statement of the main features of my uneventful trip to the home Station—to procure sledge runner—while a member of your northern sledge party in March and April of this year. We, as you will remember, left Lincoln Bay for the North at 6:30 p.m. April 1st, and the false start resulting in our misfortune at Cape Union—and our return to the snowhouse, occupy five and a half hours. Another hour was passed in waiting for the ramekin of tea you prepared for us making preparation after which —at 10 am., April 2nd I started accompanied by Jens. We took with us the shoe of our broken runner as I thought it would expedite the work at Fort Conger. Our outfit was extremely simple consisting of a small spirit lamp, a small quantity of spirits, and sufficient processed meat and chocolate for a lunch. We also carried large knives with which to dig ourselves a burrow in the hard snow should be overtaken by storm or accident before reaching the first possible stopping place—the snowhouse at Shift Rudder Bay. The thermometer when we started -42, and the sun was just appearing above the rough icy horizon to the north pouring a flood of light down the straits and consorting and glistening on the hummocks and icepoints in our path, in a manner that caused us to lose sight of the beauty of the scene, in the discomfort experienced in the effect upon our eyes. It was difficult for us to wear the snow goggles as the condensing moisture obscured our vision and rendered our step uncertain.</p>
<p>Thinking we could effect a shorter route by foot over the Bay then that necessarily taken by the loaded sledges we struck across directly for the bold point of Cape Frederick VII. We soon found ourselves completely beset by snowdrifts and hummocks and were glad to see the original path as indicated by the marks of the sledge. We traveled rapidly checking our pace only when an alternative in carrying the shoe and examined our faces which sometimes required the application of a warm hand to efface the white seal of Jack Frost. Considerable elation was felt when our stopping place at Wrangle Bay—representing one days march while outward hummocks, rubble ice and snowdrifts at the entrance to Wrangle Bay. We sometimes fell in with the bear tracks and inadvertently following them for a short distance found the traveling so much improved that we unhesitatingly followed them through the intricacies of the ice along the ice foot. The advantages of Bruin’s superior icepilotage partly condoned his offence in eating our pemmican. We began to weary about the time Cape Beechy was doubled and the remaining four miles, along the long course of Shift Rudder Bay was made with much difficulty. Jens who before had always a reassuring smile and shake of the head for answer to my “tired Jens” now began to answer less confidently and soon replied with a strong affirmative, although reminded me when his tum for carrying the shoe came. The walking from Cape Beechy to depot “B” was most tiresome — although smoother— as the frosty, sandy snow resting on the ice furnished a very unstable foothold for our polished moccasins at each step slipped back half the stride already too short. Despite our strong desire to move, our progress, without occasional rest, was not easy to make, and a line of small decayed hummocks fringing our road- furnished us with resting places. So soon as we would touch the icy seat I would find myself dozing and would find Jens with his hand on his heart or lying full length upon the snow fast asleep. When near depot “B” Jens pushed to stop and rest, but I induced him to move along until within a few hundred yards of our destination. I then left him lying in the snow and hastened to the hut intending to look to him so soon as a fire was started. He joined me in about 20 minutes. Doubtless Jens exhaustion was due to the greater exertions and worry he had undergone in getting the dogs with the broken sledge back to Lincoln Bay for I am sure that his powers of endurance are greater than mine. We reached the snowhouse at 2:30 p.m.—altogether traveling 19 hours traveling and covering at least 40 miles. it is difficult to state exactly the distance traveled as our route was necessarily serpentine and tortuous through the ice and a long detour had to be made in getting out of Lincoln Bay</p>
<p>We turned in a sleeping bag after a hasty meal of baked beans which we gave hardly time to thaw. I intended resuming the march in a few hours—so soon as we were rested—but did not succeed in waking up until 8 oclock next morning (April 3rd).</p>
<p>Our foot gear we had trusted to the influence of the stove, but found so frozen we were compelled to return to the sleeping bag and nurse them back to state sufficiently flexible to admit of putting them on our feet. We started for home Station at 11 a.m. Attempted several short cuts to shorten the 18 1/2 miles between us and home, but with the exception of the one across Brenta Bay, found the traveling more difficult than if we had followed the icefoot. At St.&nbsp;Patrick’s Bay, especially, did we fare badly. The weather was very (pleasant) compelling us to doff our (tirmiaks) (parkas) and carry them suspended to our belts. Our sudden and unexpected arrival at Fort Conger causes some considerable excitement and apprehension for our safety. On reporting to our Commanding officer he at once ordered the work on sledge runner to commence, and it was continued up to midnight. We learned that the large North Greenland sledge party had just departed and I had missed meeting them by cutting across country from Watercourse Bay, while they followed the coast around Distant Cape.</p>
<p>On Thursday April 4th after another good meal surrounded by the comparatively luxurious appointments of Fort Conger Jens and I started back to join you. The sledge runner has completed as Lt. Greely made the arrangement so advantageous to us that it would follow us to Depot “B” with Lt. Lockwood who was to start in a few hours with Jewell, Frederick and the dog sledge to join the main party. We arrived at Depot “B” at 11:30 p.m. after 8 hrs tramp and found the Greenland party just arrived from Depot “C” Cape Murchison where they had passed the first night. Lt. Lockwood with dog sledge arrived at 3 a.m. the next morning.</p>
<p>Wednesday April 5th at 3:30 p.m. we bid “goodbye” to the Greenlanders who had entertained us so kindly, and moved on northward. We carried the runner by supporting party of its weight allowing the end only to drag. We assumed the burden alternately and made very good time. The temperature when starting was only -22°, but the cold increased perceptively although we had no measuring its intensity. We made a detour that avoided the hummocks and gave us smoother traveling across Wrangle Bay. Stopped to ascertain the state of cache at North Side and found it undisturbed. Melted a little ice to quench our thirst and continued around Mount Parry. It was then midnight. The morning of Thursday, April 6th dawned bright and clear and we entered Lincoln Bay in a blaze of light. On nearing the snowhouse Jens was received with more than three cheers by his dogs and a few moments later I was giving you the latest news from Fort Conger.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-04-02/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 20:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1882-03-23:1882-04-01</title>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-03-23/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="thursday-march-23rd-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-march-23rd-1882">Thursday March 23rd 1882</h2>
<p>We spent a sleepless and uncomfortable night at temperature outside at -40. We had no effectual way of closing the entrance to the hut and the cold air entered without difficulty. Dr.&nbsp;cooked breakfast after which we went to the English depot of rations and overhauled it. It was well snowed over and compelled us to use the shovel a great deal but was otherwise in good condition. Jewell and his team of dogs with driver having supported as far as had been arranged started to return to the Station at 12 p.m. He took with him 140 lbs of the canned Australian beef and a small quantity of each of the following articles: onion paste, curry powder and tobacco. I was much interested in the manner in which the two Eskimos parted company. They were fully aware that at least two months would elapse before they would again meet and were also sensible of the dangers to be passed before that time, yet no word or action passed between them to show that any unusual feeling was entertained. I vainly watched for some break in their stoical demeanor. They parted without even a glance at being exchanged although I know they are sincerely attached to each other. It is proof of that strange negative character so happily described by the observant Dr. Hayes.</p>
<p>After Jewell was out of sight we spent the afternoon in picking out of the depot the stores we intend to use. We also made some improvements in our snowhouse building a vestibule of snow blocks to add to the warmth. Also made a walk to pick out the most favorable path for the morrow. At 7 p.m. the thermometer stood at -39.5.</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-march-24th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-march-24th-1882">Friday March 24th 1882</h2>
<p>The sleeping bag occupied by Jens and I was originally intended for one man —a fat Governor in Greenland. For reducing our constant weights of load to the minimum before started we concluded that by inserting a wedge shaped extension it would accommodate two of us and save the trouble of carrying a bag for each. This furry envelope naturally fell to the lot of Jens and I, the smallest ones of the trio, and when we tried it at the Station—with lighter clothing on—it appeared large enough.</p>
<p>Our experience in the field however was not exactly as pleasant as we expected. This part of my journal (as will appear obvious to the most superficial observer) is written up from notes made from my sledge journal kept while on the field. I will here transcribe verbatim my entry made on this date: Did not spend a very pleasant night, sleeping bag too small for two of us and Jens and I have much difficulty in squeezing into it after which “spooning” we can only turn by concerted movement. Other movements are impossible. Fortunately Jens is much shorter than | and our straddled feet reach different depths in the bag. The door of the snowhouse open with temperatures outside of -56.2 (88 ° below freezing point). Dr.&nbsp;and Jens got up at 4 a.m. I at 5 a.m. I am now at 6 a.m. writing this outside and a glance at thermometer shows the temperature at -45°. Have been wrestling for some time with my termiak which resembles a coat of sheet iron and in my frantic efforts to put it on have split it down the back—(imagine the hieroglyphics in which above entry was made in my diary with pencil held in band encased in a dogskin mitten as large as a sofa pillow) — to continue later: –</p>
<p>We started north at 8 a.m. with heavy load. “Redeye” one of the dogs being too big with pups was left behind in the snowhouse to which we will return after advancing our load some distance up the coast. Temp at start -42°, at 11 a.m. -39. At noon brisk breeze sprung up from 8. East and had so increased by 5:30 p.m. as to force us into camp as the traveling was bad and drifting snow prevented us from seeing the way.</p>
<p>The traveling during the day generally good although we were compelled to shift from icefoots to straits and back again several times and had to unpack the load twice and carry it over obstructions. The load was very heavy and when we stopped dogs appeared tired.</p>
<p>We pitched our tents in a lee of a large hummock in the Straits, about 50 yds from the icefoot. Dr.&nbsp;cooks supper while Jens and I feed dog and secure tents which increasing wind endangers. At 6 a.m. temp -36° 1/2. As we were eating our stew and drinking chocolate, the clouds of condensed vapor condensing and congealing against the top of the tent, fallen again in a miniature snow storm covering clothes and sleeping bags in a white sheet while it also falls down our backs and in other ways aggravates us.</p>
<p>Thrusting my hand in the bag of ice Jens brought in I found the pieces like coals of fire and withdrew it with the ice sticking as if like butter.</p>
<p>I have two toes suffering from frostbite and the fingers of all three of us are more or less frost burnt.</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-march-25th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-march-25th-1882">Saturday March 25th 1882</h2>
<p>The wind increased during the night and at the usual time for starting it was so strong that we thought it best to lay over for a few hours. At 12 noon we got up and after some time in prospecting for a lead out of the labyrinth of ice by which we were surrounded, we took to the icefoot which in this place is piled up in double serrated lines as if created at different times. We were compelled to carry the light load with which we started, piecemeal over about 75 yds. and in places had to cut footholds in the slippery wall. We left our tent standing with sleeping bags and cooking utensils intending to return to camp. The wind blew briskly although much moderated, but fortunately in our backs. We reached Black cape at 8 p.m. Storms still light and from an (elevated) icy pinnacle we could see a way to the North on the frozen sea, a low dark streak that so resembled land that had we been the first to gaze in that direction we should probably make the mistake of the Polaris people who placed “Presidents Land” where later parties found a sea of ice. It was probably a dark stratus cloud or some other illusory phenomenon.</p>
<p>We started to return after caching our load and reached the tent at midnight. Temp when we started -27: while we were away -36, now midnight -32. Milatook was run over by the sledge but the hardy mutt does not look any the worse for it.</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-march-26th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-march-26th-1882">Sunday March 26th 1882</h2>
<p>Temp during night—or morning– -37° 5. We started back to Lincoln Bay at 10:30 a.m. with a strong breeze blowing and with temp of -33°. We had much difficulty in keeping our noses from freezing. Poor noses! They are already swollen and scarified by Jack Frost and our clumsy attempts to protect them with our dogskin mittens brought the tears to our eyes—how gladly would the Arctic travelers dispense with this troublesome organ while sledging! We arrived at snowhouse, Lincoln Bay, at 4:30 p.m. wind had gone down. Temp at 5 p.m. -34.5 “Redeye” ok, but not yet a mother.</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-march-27th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-march-27th-1882">Monday March 27th 1882</h2>
<p>Min temp during night -44: at 10 a.m. when we started back to our tent near Cape Union (false) it had risen to -23. We had a considerable load but got along swimmingly. The morning was beautiful calm and clear—“too fine to last” as the Dr. remarked. About noon a light breeze sprang up from the south and kept steadily increasing until between 2 and 3 o’clock p.m. It was blowing a gale and we became anxious to reach the tent for shelter. We also feared it might be blown away before we could reach it.</p>
<p>The barometer was falling alarmingly fast and the temperature was rising rapidly—the south gale bringing warm weather.</p>
<p>At 4 p.m. we reached the tent still standing and fortunately sheltered by the large hummock south of it. The wind was then blowing 30 miles an hour at least and the temp was only down to -11. but even with this comparatively (warm) temperature we could never have made the latter part of our days journey if the gale had not been in our back for the searching wind pierced our forms and the face could not be turned toward it except for the shortest possible space of time. We had a very unpleasant time making our arrangements for the night, feeding the dogs, etc. At 6 p.m. temp - 11.5. Wind blowing hard as ever!</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-march-28th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-march-28th-1882">Tuesday March 28th 1882</h2>
<p>Spent rather an unpleasant night. The driving snow drifted against the sides of the tent collapsing it so that our space was curtailed within the limits of comfort. We were crowded upon each other and forced into cramped positions. The swaying tent surged and shaken by the gale precipitated upon us the snow formed on the inside which crept in the mouth of the sleeping bags and made our rest almost impossible. The dogs outside crowded for warmth and shelter against the tent and at times howled piteously. Min temp during the night -25. at 6 a.m. -15; at 7 a.m. -20. at 8 a.m. we started at Black Cape to add to our cache there. The wind began to moderate at 4 a.m. and became more to the Eastward. At 11 a.m., it had calmded down entirely and the weather was as smiling and beautiful as if no storm had ever disturbed the elements.</p>
<p>Our load was heavy and we were stopped repeatedly. At one time we were compelled to unload and relash the runners which occupied one hour. Temp in sun -5; in shade -18. Reached Black Cape at 3:30 p.m. Melted some ice, eat a lunch, and start to return to tent at False Cape Union where we arrive at 8 p.m.—temp: -25.</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-march-29th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-march-29th-1882">Wednesday March 29th 1882</h2>
<p>Barometer showed another remarkable fall this morning. Temp (Min) during night -43. I suffered much with pain in the limbs found on examination swollen to twice the size of the other. Sleep was impossible. Started with empty sledge for our snow home at Lincoln Bay to get the last load of provisions and maps, at 10:30 a.m. and arrived there at 2:30 p.m. Temp at 3p.m. -29. at 7p.m. it had fallen -36.5</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-march-30th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-march-30th-1882">Thursday March 30th 1882</h2>
<p>The fall of barometer was followed by what it predicted. Stormy weather this morning. Wind becoming strong from the south with clouds and drifts of snow. The minimum temperature during the night was registered was -52 but the southern storm brought it up to -15 at 12 p.m. A remarkable range!</p>
<p>Traveling was out of the question so we rigged up a (?) lamp to burn cocoanut stearine which we found in the English depot, and attempted to dry our footgear.</p>
<p>My original entry in sledge journal in evening—outside—is later; later still blowing and drifting from south with snow falling. My little finger was frozen while writing this</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-march-31st-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-march-31st-1882">Friday March 31st 1882</h2>
<p>Having slept part of the day yesterday I did not go to sleep until near morning. I laid outside the sleeping bag and kept the stearine lamp going. An old number of Litteil’s furnished me with reading matter. On starting out in the morning I found that we were completely snowed in — our vestibule full of drift. I found that I could not ignite the matches which I attributed to dampness and as the only alternative started for the English depot where we knew there were several boxes of dry ones. Had much difficulty in effecting an exit. Fortunately we had a shovel within and with it I dug my way and seeing daylight through the snowy shell forced my head and shoulder through it to the open air. While doing so I found breathing difficult and several times while shoveling I felt faint and almost unable to continue. This showed us that it was foul and nephitic air, and that it was due to this the matches would not burn.</p>
<p>The storm had ceased and only the drifts showed the effects of yesterdays storm. At 8:30 a.m. with a light load (396 lbs. of the English canned meat) we started for our tent at False Cape Union intending to return at once to our depot at Lincoln Bay for the last of our provisions which were rather heavy to add and carry in our load. Reached tent at 12:40 p.m. Started to return at 1 p.m., arrived at Lincoln again at</p>
<p>Temp at 4 p.m.-27.5 Bar. 30.39</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-april-1st-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-april-1st-1882">Saturday April 1st 1882</h2>
<p>As the season is now advanced so that the influence of the sun can be felt considerably. Dr.&nbsp;thinks it best to change our time of travel from day to night so that we may profit by the suns warmth while sleeping and also because the reflection of the night light an (?) unpleasant effect upon the eyes is not so great. We therefore decide to lay over till evening and then start (?) but rise early.</p>
<p>Minimum temp during the night -35.0 at 12 p.m. -30, at 4 p.m. 38.8</p>
<p>Dogs irrigated my satchel last night so completely I did not like to handle my sledge journal which it contained. It was lying on the sledge and being black and glazed attracted Kingatook’s attention, the other dogs faithfully following his example. We started north at 6:30 p.m. not expecting to again visit the snowhouse (Lincoln Bay) until our return homeward. Took “Redeye” along she has not had her pups and her procrastination makes it appear that she is a malingerer taking advantage of the fact that she is invalided. She looks as if she were about to present us with a full grown team of dogs, harnesses and all.</p>
<p>Getting along swimmingly and even congratulating ourselves on the fact that our work would now be on new ground in a few days, when —in passing from the ice foot to the Straits at Cape Union (a place safely passed frequently by us) the sledge bounded awkwardly from the icefoot so that on a lower level and split one runner. Our consternation was indescribable. It appeared broken beyond al! hope of repait and the Dr.&nbsp;was completely prostrate. When unloaded and dragged slowly back to the snowhouse carrying nothing but sleeping bags and cooking gear. The sledge pulled in its broken state, awkwardly and slowly. Reached snowhouse at about midnight</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-03-23/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 19:45:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1882-03-15:1882-03-22</title>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-03-15/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="wednesday-march-15th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-march-15th-1882">Wednesday March 15th 1882</h2>
<p>I was busy all day making some more photographs and preparing for our start on Saturday. I made one negative of dogs hauling ice which turned out very well, the dogs having kept perfectly still during the exposure. Lt.’s Kislingbury and Greely and also Cross and Jens were included in the group.</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-march-16th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-march-16th-1882">Thursday March 16th 1882</h2>
<p>Almost crazed getting ready for our start. Clothing to be collected, cooking gear to look after, etc. The Dr.&nbsp;has taken a wise plan; he and I had made a complete list of all that we are required to take and divided this again and each of us looking up and preparing the articles set down on our list and checking the same when added to our pile in the lean-to. The brains are racked to remember every little thing as anything left behind cannot be replaced.</p>
<p>Max: -32.1 Min: -42.2.</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-march-17th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-march-17th-1882">Friday March 17th 1882</h2>
<p>Was a cold St Patrick’s day, Max:-30.6 Min:-35.6</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-march-18th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-march-18th-1882">Saturday March 18th 1882</h2>
<p>Our preparations are now complete and will start tomorrow morning. A good dinner and a quart of ardent enlivened the last evening we shall spend under roof for some time.</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-march-19th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-march-19th-1882">Sunday March 19th 1882</h2>
<p>This morning at 9:40 a.m. accompanied by Jewell and Fred the Esquimaux we made our start for the North. Jewell will return after supporting us as far as Lincoln Bay. Our party will then consist of but three persons, Dr.&nbsp;Pavy, myself and the driver Jens. Nine dogs to our team and 8 to Jewells. The morning was cloudy and a little blustery but afterwards improved. I made a photograph of the outfit including myself also in the picture with Gardiner to make the exposure. Lt. Kislingbury walked with us as far as Cape Murchison where he bade us “Godspeed” and we pursued our way. Temp when started was only -24 but was ten degrees lower when we reached Depot “B” at Shift Rudder Bay where we arrived at 3:40 p.m.</p>
<p>We found the party of seven just returned from Greenland shore. Their experience was a very trying and unpleasant one, and the temperatures they were called to withstand were probably lower than have ever been recorded by parties in the field. When their first camp was made the temp stood -53 and during the night fell below -61 the point at which their thermometer was graduated and below which there was no registry—the index point was forced below the scale and stood in the bulb. Schneider gave up first day out from Depot “B” and was sent back to the snowhouse with Biederbeck with nurse (see sledge journal) not one of the party has escaped injured fingers and scarified noses and cheeks. The large party crowded us out of the snowhouse so Jewell and I dug a hole in a large bank of closely packed snow and in this we passed a fairly comfortable night. At an early hour we were aroused by the seven sleepers arriving at our igloo to bid us goodbye and we drowsily pulled aside the flap of our sleeping bags to reply to their salutation. Lynn crawled on top of our fragile crystal palace to shout his good wishes the ventilation hole in the roof. To show a proper amount of appreciation we turned our faces, Jewell and I, in the direction from which the sound issued, when crash came a swaddled foot through the snowy chill precipitating on our smiling upturned faces clouds and huge blocks of frosty snow. Lynn avers that he saw clouds of sulphur escape as he beat a hasty retreat to join his companions. Temp at midnight in hut -1 outside the thermometer was —39.</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-march-20th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-march-20th-1882">Monday March 20th 1882</h2>
<p>After the early start of Brainards party for the home Station we got another nap. Started at 10 a.m.: the day gloomy and unpleasant. We found the traveling on ice foot very good for some distance when we were compelled to take to the strait where to ice was rough beyond description. The piled up masses of ice disputed our right of way on the ice foot, and the straits were only to be traveled over the most disruptive of rubble ice crushed into the greatest irregularity and unevenness by the tides and currents in the fall before the frost cemented it together. It conveyed more the impression of a stormy sea lashed into fury and frozen instantly into immobility. Temp during day 20 below zero but with a SE blowing made traveling very uncomfortable. Snow began to fall and at 6:30 p.m. had so increased that we could not see our way and so went into camp on the icefoot between Cape Beechy and Wrangle Bay. Jewell and I dug snowhouse while Dr.&nbsp;and Jens fed the dogs. The moment we camped they curled themselves like hedgehogs and the snow dusting about them soon enveloped them in a white sheet beneath which they slept until the smell of chopped pemmican brought them to their feet when it necessary for one of the drivers, me, to keep them in abeyance while the others scattered the food in the snow. The restraint was then withdrawn when there was a rush—snarl—and the frozen meal was dispatched at almost one gulp by the wolfish animals. They then burrowed again the snow where they remained quiet until near morning when they were sufficiently rested to again prance around disturbing our rest by their snarling at and quarreling with each other. The dogs of one team appeared to be the sworn enemies of the other and woe betide the luckless dog that wanders into the enemies camp. Unless his friends, generalled by the King dog, can come to the rescue, a sad remnant of caninity is all that will be left to hobble back to his comrades. Barometer has been falling all day.</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-march-21st-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-march-21st-1882">Tuesday March 21st 1882</h2>
<p>Weather was still thick and threatening when we emerged from our burrow in the snow this morning. We did not get started before noon. The temp was mild -10, but the wind was still blowing. We had great difficulty in proceeding, the high tides harassing us along the icefoot. (I) know of nothing I can compare the nature of ice to. I have never seen rocks on land so dispersed as to make so uneven a surface as the rubble ice over which we traveled. One of us would advance with an axe to pick out a route and reduce obstructions when necessary. The other, one at the upstanders steering and pushing, the driver at the lines winding the dogs through the narrow openings among the hummocks and rubble, followed slowly and laboriously and notwithstanding our care the sledges (were) upset twice and the runner of Jens so wrenched that it was necessary to unload and relash it. It is surprising the amount of rough usage the Esk. sledges will stand. They are put together entirely with lashings of walrus hide and when loaded—as they were—with over 600 Ibs. each, they will go over a track of such roughness that the dogs themselves have to climb and jump over the obstacle. One runner will glide up over a sharp block of ice from a few feet high while the other falls in some crevice below. The whole weight is thrown on the latter which is turned over on its side until it touches the crosspieces. Presently the sledge will emerge bound off into a smooth place and land on its feet like a cat—the elastic thongs bringing the runner again vertically under the sledge.</p>
<p>We arrived at Wrangle Bay at 7:30 and for the first time since leaving the Station erected our tent which—intended to accommodate three—was too small to shelter us all and Jewell and I made a small hole in the snow, just large enough to admit of spreading out the sleeping bag where we spent a rather uncomfortable night with the temp at only -24. My knees were swollen and rather stiff which made me fear a possible attack of my old enemy the “acute”: but the morning reassured me to a certain extent.</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-march-22nd-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-march-22nd-1882">Wednesday March 22nd 1882</h2>
<p>Today after threading our way through some very rough ice we reached a large floe of the paleocrystic ice of Sir George. On this ice the snow was sufficiently glazed and hard to bear the sledges. We stopped at Mount Parry to pick up the cache of provisions left there by the Dr.&nbsp;last autumn. On approaching the place we found the tracks of large polar bear and on examination of the cache found that the brute had eaten almost all the pemmican. He had also torn open the bag containing the hard tack: but on not finding the contents palatable had scattered them among the snow and turned his attention to the pemmican of which he made a lunch of almost 70 lbs!</p>
<p>Gathering up the remnants of the depot we proceeded, finding the traveling very good over a strip of young ice that extended for a few miles towards Cape Frederick VII. The icefront along this place presented a most remarkable appearance. It was fully fifty feet high in an almost perpendicular wall and must have been created under great pressure. The surface on which the sun blazed and glistened was as polished and resplendent as a silver rampart studded with jewels.</p>
<p>We soon passed off the young ice and traveled over a succession of paleocrystic floes which afforded even better travel than the season ice which was covered with a salty effluence that made traction difficult. The only difficulty we experienced was in passing from one floe to another where the edges were askew and piled up, but even here the snow had drifted so that we could almost always find a place where the chasm between the floes was edged over.</p>
<p>At 1 p.m. it was so calm and still that we stopped a short time to melt some ice and quench our thirst. We were so comfortable and the weather looked so pleasant that we were surprised to find that it was 36° below zero. We encountered some rough traveling before we camped in Lincoln Bay about one mile north of the English depot at 5:30 p.m. Jewell and I set to work to build another snowhouse on which we spent two or three hours before its dimensions and finish suited us. We spent the (more) time because we knew that it was to be our headquarters for some time while we are advancing our provisions along the coast to the North.</p>
<p>Temperature at 6 p.m. was -35°</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-03-15/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 19:45:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1882-03-08:1882-03-14</title>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-03-08/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="wednesday-march-8th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-march-8th-1882">Wednesday March 8th 1882</h2>
<p>The subject of gas was agitated considerably today. The effects of the gas evolved from our stove has become a matter of grave importance. There are few of us who have not felt the pernicious effects of it—spending so much time indoors as we are compelled to do—and it is time some change was made in the stove’s pipe to prevent it. Temp. Max: -32.2, Min: -37.6, Mean: -34.27</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-march-9th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-march-9th-1882">Thursday March 9th 1882</h2>
<p>Lt. Greely sent me with Connell and Biederbeck to Lake Alexander (actually Alexandra) to ascertain the thickness of the ice there. Ralston accompanied us as far as Mt. Ovibus which he ascended to get a view to the N.W. towards United States Range. We had a cold time of it; were 9 hours gone and had our noses frozen repeatedly. We were several hours getting through the ice which we found to be 80 inches in thickness.</p>
<p>We were compelled to commence with a large hole at the surface so that there would be room to work when the hole deepened. At last the digger found the ice above his head on all sides. We found that Dr.&nbsp;Pavy and Linn had retumed from the Greenland side having deposited their provisions in Gap Valley.</p>
<p>Linn gave me an instance of Jens toughness: Linn, after one of the hardest days work traveling through a storm was so completely tired out that he at once crawled in the double sleeping bag and fell asleep. Jens, after attending to the dogs, came in the tent to sleep but supposing Linn to be ill, laid outside the bag all night. He must have spent a terrible night as the temperature was below -40!</p>
<p>Crazy Jane,—one of the dogs, called Milatook by the drivers, — amused us very much with her antics when a seal skin shoe was placed on her sore foot. She had the most ludicrous manner of holding it up and inspecting it. Lt. Greely made the ascent of Cairn Hill. Henry complains of rheumatic pain and Israel takes his place on observations.</p>
<p>Max: -26.1, Min: -36.6. Mean: -31.7</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-march-10th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-march-10th-1882">Friday March 10th 1882</h2>
<p>Bean dryer to work all day. Weather comparatively warm. I walked down with Dr.&nbsp;and we talk over plan for his northern trip. Linn’s experience with canvas boots does not encourage us much to believe in their suitability.</p>
<p>Temp Max: -18.8 Min: 29.7 Mean: -23.05</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-march-11th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-march-11th-1882">Saturday March 11th 1882</h2>
<p>I was testing some thread for Lt. G to see if it could support sufficient weight to allow it to be used for deep sea sounding.</p>
<p>Israel and I took sea temperatures and measured thickness of ice in harbor. Max: -10.7 , Min: -18.9. Mean:-13.19</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-march-12th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-march-12th-1882">Sunday March 12th 1882</h2>
<p>I went to Distant Cape and from there proceeding some distance on the ice to ascertain if it was fit to travel on in the direction of Polaris Bay. Connell accompanied me. Found the walking very bad and did not proceed further than 2 or 3 miles in the Strait. The traveling across from Distant Cape to Thank God Harbor is almost impracticable. I should advise a person crossing to start at Cape Murchison as the floes appear to be larger and less hummocky. We found the hummocks closely packed and soft snow dumped between. A strong breeze sprang up as we started to return. Lifting the snow in blinding sheets. Fortunately it was in our backs: it would have been impossible to proceed to the fort had it been in our faces. We arrived at the Station badly frozen up: faces coated with frozen snow and temiaks as stiff as sheet iron.</p>
<p>In the evening Lt. Greely had some conversation with almost all the members of the party, eliciting their wishes or willingness to go on the arduous sledge trips. To the credit of all it must be said that great enthusiasm was shown; everyone quite anxious to take part in the exciting 1f dangerous and arduous work. The commanding officer asked me to take some photographs of the party before we start out. The Dr. and I will start on 18th of this month. Later Lt. G interviewed me in regard to my correspondence to NY Herald—see private journal.</p>
<p>Max: -8.9, Min: 29.8, Mean: 21.31</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-march-13th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-march-13th-1882">Monday March 13th 1882</h2>
<p>Everyone is busy today preparing the party to start for Greenland side with boat and provisions; the boat to remain as a safeguard for the later party to return in case the Straits are broken or open. Brainard, Biederbeck, Schneider, Elison Connell, Whistler and Linn will compose the party. They will gone seven days at least. I made some negatives of the launch and ice foot. But in developing I found that the light was still too weak.</p>
<p>Max: 29.9 Min: 36.6 Mean: 34.94</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-march-14th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-march-14th-1882">Tuesday March 14th 1882</h2>
<p>The party mentioned above started today. I accompanied them to Distant Cape with Eskimo and dog sledge carrying part of their load. They all started off in good spirits. I was much amused by Whistler’s request for fifteen leisure before starting to commune with his photograph of some frontier inamorata of his whom he designated as “Broncho Moll”. —see private journal.</p>
<p>My Eskimo Jens brought me back at a terrific rate using the 20 foot leash to great advantage. Rushing through the cold air was like facing a biting breeze and in spite of all my efforts I froze both cheeks. I found that the temperature had fallen ten degrees while I was gone! Max: -35.3 Min: -45.3 Mean: 38.08</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-03-08/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 19:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1882-02-23:1882-03-07</title>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-02-23/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="thursday-february-23rd-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-february-23rd-1882">Thursday February 23rd 1882</h2>
<p>I hauled my quota of ice. The quarters have become a perfect Babel or worse. The tinner, carpenter, tentmaker and shoemaker are all busily engaged at their several callings preparing the foot gear, sledges, lamps and other paraphernalia for the eagerly-looked-forward to spring explorations.</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-february-24th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-february-24th-1882">Friday February 24th 1882</h2>
<p>Linn, Connell and Biederbeck went to the coal mines to mine some coals. I went along with gun hoping to get a shot at my hare. The caracaturist of our party has embellished the wall with a drawing representing my surprise at seeing the “kangaroo.”</p>
<p>I was gone five hours and saw nothing in the way of game. I succeeded however, in freezing my cheeks and nose. The weather is slightly warmer.</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-february-25th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-february-25th-1882">Saturday February 25th 1882</h2>
<p>Hauled ice. Took a walk with Dr — see P J</p>
<p>Several parties were out hunting as the light has now become so bright as to make it safe and pleasant. The quarters still present the appearance of a machine shop. A boat which Cross is painting bas been added to the stock. The temperature has taken a remarkable rise.</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-february-26-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-february-26-1882">Sunday February 26, 1882</h2>
<p>A quiet Sabbath. The light has increased so that today the idea of beholding ourselves by natural instead of artificial light occurred to some of us. We were all perplexed at the bleached out appearance of our countenances.</p>
<p>I was much amused at the consternation of the old “Kingatoon” — our boss dog — when I showed him his “counterfeit presentment” in a mirror: he showed fight at once. I took a walk with Schneider and the pups.</p>
<p>Jewell with driver and dog team made a trip to Murchison and back taking some stores.</p>
<p>A very quiet evening after the rum passed around.</p>
<p>I indulge in some reflections of a sentimental, slushy nature — see private journal.</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-february-27th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-february-27th-1882">Monday February 27th 1882</h2>
<p>Henry’s birthday; a good bill of fare. Lt. Greely tells me to prepare for taking observations.</p>
<p>Ralston and Schneider go to Bellot Island to read the meteorological instruments.</p>
<p>They see a hare. I go on duty at midnight.</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-february-28th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-february-28th-1882">Tuesday February 28th 1882</h2>
<p>The sky this morning was of a most beautiful rose color, predicting the appearance of the sun which showed its upper limit at 11.40 a.m. The whole disk was seen from 11:45 to 11:57</p>
<p>Gardiner, Connell and I — just coming off observations miss seeing the returning luminary. The prodigal sun was just seen by Dr.&nbsp;Pavy. Ralston and Henry who met him at the top of Cairn Hill before he lighted up our somber dwelling. I believe it is the rule to indulge in some attempt at poetical allusion to the eagerly wished for return of Old Sol: but for the most rosily beautiful description of the event to be found in arctic literature commend me to Hayes’ gem of a paragraph which discourages any attempt at imitation as completely as the effluguent rays of the glorious sun pales the feeble light of the silvery moon.” It made the moon sick” was the rather inelegant comment of Whistler.</p>
<p>Whistler by the way went gunning today and joining a snow slide goes whirling down one of the precipitous bluffs of Bellot Island. He suffers no greater injury than the wearing out of his pants. The United States Govt. however, sustains the loss of a rifle which was broken in the catastrophe.</p>
<p>Bender is quite unwell. He is troubled with his lungs and I fear will hardly endure two winters here. Temp -47.6 Mean: -39.69</p>
<p>A small party are making preparations to cross over to Hall’s rest.</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-march-1st-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-march-1st-1882">Wednesday March 1st 1882</h2>
<p>Lt. Lockwood, Jewell and Brainard with Frederick and the dog team start for the Greenland coast by way of Beechy. Long goes to support them so far as Beechy with Jens and the other team. Their object is to examine the condition of the provisions left by Polaris and English party on the other side to decide to what extent they can be depended upon for the sledge journey in the spring.</p>
<p>The quarters are still lumbered up with lumber, sledges, boats, canvas shoes, etc. Cross is at present wholly engaged in keeping the boat painted red. While he decorates one side the other is kept bare for him by the loose trousers of the passerby. Our pants all appear to be of the same material now—at least they are all red.</p>
<p>Light snow, sun obscured. I have not yet seen the sun. Henry discovered a fly in the vessel of rum that has been placed in the observatory to show the effect of low temperatures. It must have been blown from the cracks of the observatory where it has probably lain since the structure was made in “God’s country.”</p>
<p>Some members of the party — strange to say — go much further to explain the presence of the insect. They all agree however that the fly’s lives had “fallen in pleasant places”. Brainard has found a petrification.</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-march-2nd-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-march-2nd-1882">Thursday March 2nd 1882</h2>
<p>I start with Connell and Ellis to see if the musk ox meat there is alright. A cold tramp took us to the tripod I erected last autumn; but instead of two fine carcasses I left suspended there, there was two skeletons of great value, no doubt, to the anatomist, but of no value to us, nicely prepared by the wolves and foxes.</p>
<p>Not wishing to have our trip entirely without any useful result, I hauled a bag of coal from the mine down to the ice foot. We arrived at the Station at 5 p.m. Dr. Pavy, Linn and Henry have brought in the petrification which appears to be the section of a large pine tree. This is an opening for all manner of conjectures as regards the former condition of this region — now so completely barren of vegetation.</p>
<p>Lt. Kislingbury and Israel go to Mt. Campbell. They saw a hare but did not get within range. Long returns at 5 pm: states that Lt. Lockwood and party started to cross the channel at Beechy this morning. Temp. Min: -35.8, Max: -27.6, Mean:-</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-march-3rd-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-march-3rd-1882">Friday March 3rd 1882</h2>
<p>No sun today. I therefore gave up my notion of ascending Cairn Hill. Light snow during the afternoon. Bender is better. Connell was out hunting. More red paint. Temp Min: -36.5 Max: -26.5, Mean: -31.7</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-march-4th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-march-4th-1882">Saturday March 4th 1882</h2>
<p>Cloudy and sunny weather today. Biederbeck and I walked to Dutch Island and returned about 4 p.m. It was then quite stormy in the Straits.</p>
<p>No sun — Dr.&nbsp;asked me to walk after dinner and he talked over plans for the North trip — see private journal — -Max:- 32.1 , - Min: 38.6, Mean: -34.9</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-march-5th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-march-5th-1882">Sunday March 5th 1882</h2>
<p>It snowed last night but cleared up this morning and Dr.&nbsp;Pavy and Linn with dog team and driver Jens started for Cape Sumner Greenland to carry provisions for the use of the sledging party which will go in that direction. They started at 7:45 a.m. Connell and I started up Cairn Hill to get a view of the strait. We had a cold time of it the temperature was about -40 and a good breeze blowing making the cold almost unbearable. I would sooner endure -70 and calm than have -25 and the air in motion, Whistler and Salor walked around Bellot Island.</p>
<p>While on Cairn Hill with Connell I saw the glorious sun for the first time in 142 days. Old Sol has been due for 6 or 7 days, but the bad weather, has kept from me the pleasure of seeing him. Although I am the only member of the party who did not see it on the 28th Feb.</p>
<p>It was a glorious sight that can only be appreciated by those who have passed through a long night of four months. See something slushy on this subject in private diary this date. A quite dreary Sunday night, snowy and drifting outside and thoughts of home and friends crowding thick and fast upon us as we listened around the fire.</p>
<p>Temp Max: -28.6 Min: -44.1, Mean: -36.04</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-march-6th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-march-6th-1882">Monday March 6th 1882</h2>
<p>Storm still continues. As soon as the snow ceased to fall a party dragged the small boat “Discovery” — one left by the English out to Distant Cape. We are certainly fortunate in the selection of winter quarters here.</p>
<p>The wind was (blowing) but one mile per hour while at the same time the anemometer at Dutch Island registered 22 miles an hour. Temp -27.0, -36.5., 30.18</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-march-7th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-march-7th-1882">Tuesday March 7th 1882</h2>
<p>Lt. Kislingbury shot two hares today. The light is increasing daily. At 5 a.m. this is quite a bright twilight. Temp. Min: -44.7, Max: -22.8, Mean: -37.0</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-02-23/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1882-02-09:1882-02-22</title>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-02-09/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="thursday-february-9th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-february-9th-1882">Thursday February 9th 1882</h2>
<p>The light steadily increasing and has suggested the coming field work. Lt. Greely therefore inaugurates the preparation for it by setting Bender to work making spirit lamps and cooking utensils. Fredericks our saddler is set to work experimenting with foot gear. This is rendered necessary by our almost total destitution of anything suitable for traveling on the sledge journeys that are contemplated. After much discussion and cussin’ they decide on a combination of canvas and blanket (see private journal). Biederbeck is rolling piles of wire. Beautiful effect of land of polar Clouds. Lt. Greely favors us with a lecture on “Storms”. Temp. Max. -47.1 min. - 54.8, Mean -50.60</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-february-10th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-february-10th-1882">Friday February 10th 1882</h2>
<p>Nothing noteworthy occurs. The extreme low temperature ceases to Provoke any comments. Temp for 24 hours today was -50°.below zero, Max. -51.1, Min.-54.1, Mean -52.40</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-february-11th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-february-11th-1882">Saturday February 11th 1882</h2>
<p>At 2 a.m. I happened to be awake and the observer on duty informed me that the thermometer corrected —stood (at) —Sixty -60°1. Difference of temperature between inside and out over 110° ! I spent the day in experimenting with some lamps—finding the shortest time in which they would melt ice, etc.</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-february-12th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-february-12th-1882">Sunday February 12th 1882</h2>
<p>Our usual Sabbath—distinguished from the other days of the week by Bible readings in the morning and rum at night. The latter infuses a little harmless hilarity which finds vent in some chorus singing and violin music.</p>
<p>The weather still continues cold. (See private journal this date)</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-february-13th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-february-13th-1882">Monday February 13th 1882</h2>
<p>A very busy day—the coldest also. Lt. Lockwood, Ralston and Brainard went to Bellot Island to read the meteorological instruments left there. I tested some nine of Bender’s spirit lamp and got satisfactory results from some of the them. About the time Lt. Lockwood and the party were expected back I started out with Frederick and the dog team to meet them. Missed them as they took a new route back.</p>
<p>Lt. Greely has been experimenting to discover the rapidity with which sound travels in this country. I assisted him by discharging firearms at a distance of a mile and a half mile from him. He noted the flash and catches the sound, recording the same with aid of chronograph. 1 mile 4 1/2 sec: 1/2 mile 2 1/4.</p>
<p>In the evening Lt. Greely conversed with me in regard to my going out on sledge trips in the spring. He was good enough to say I could have command of party supporting Lt. Lockwood—an important mission in his estimation. The Dr.&nbsp;has for some time expressed a strong wish to have me accompany him and I am more desirous of going North on this side than of following the Greenland coast on the other. I think the chances of attaining the highest latitude are greater, I so expressed myself and Lt. Greely kindly allowed me to choose.</p>
<p>For particulars—private journal this date. I spent the evening in reading Hayes the most charming writer of arctic literature I have yet read.</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-february-14th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-february-14th-1882">Tuesday February 14th 1882</h2>
<p>St.&nbsp;Valentine’s day: probably the most remarkable anniversary of the day that any of us experienced. Our mail did not arrive: so our love missives and caricatures did not arrive in time to awaken our affections or wound our vanity. I hauled ice and experimented further with sound.</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-february-15th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-february-15th-1882">Wednesday February 15th 1882</h2>
<p>More experiments with the shotgun and chronograph. The results of our experiments will not, I fear, throw much light on the science of acoustics.</p>
<p>In using the guns at this low temperature we have found that all the oil must be removed from all parts of them as it freezes and will not allow the weapon to work.</p>
<p>One of our Nimrods was greatly chagrined to find on drawing bead on 4 hare—that the trigger could not be pulled. The hare walked leisurely off while he was frantically trying to get his gun off.</p>
<p>Jens shoots a hare. It is a much larger animal than I supposed: in fact I believe that the hares are larger than the foxes in this part of the world.</p>
<p>In the eve I was out with Dr.&nbsp;Pavy and Lt. Kislingbury (see private journal). I hauled ice with Jens and the dogs during the day. Weather still cold.</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-february-16th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-february-16th-1882">Thursday February 16th 1882</h2>
<p>Brainard and Cross go to Bellot Island and hare-hunting: but do not bag any. Frederick the Esquimaux has better luck bringing back a fine specimen. After Jens and I our usual quantities of ice, he, Jens, emulates Frederick’s example and returns with a duplicate hare. Hare stew in prospective. The light is daily increasing: the cold weather still continues however.</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-february-17th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-february-17th-1882">Friday February 17th 1882</h2>
<p>I make some further experiments with some new tinware of Jakay’s. I note time required to melt ice, boil the water, raise same in upper tin to given temperature, etc. I also note the amt alcohol used. The results were generally satisfactory. I hauled ice as usual; in fact I would dislike to give up this 2 hours exercise with the dog teams. It is both exhilarating and healthful. The dogs are a never failing source of interest to me. The more one uses them the better does he appreciate their usefulness and intelligence. I am getting so I can use the whip quite effectively: and succeed in communicating the strange sounding words with which the Esquimaux guide them— with some degree of resemblance to Jens. I still, however, elicit a provoking smile from the superior “whip.”</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-february-18th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-february-18th-1882">Saturday February 18th 1882</h2>
<p>Brainard yesterday ascertained that 2,200 lbs of the musk oxen meat still remains. This is agreeable intelligence as the meat is excellent and while it lasts we will laugh at scurvy.</p>
<p>Nothing noteworthy occurs today.</p>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;informs me that he has requested of Lt. Greely that I accompany him North. Dog driving is now something that I must give more attention than ever as the event may occur when the accomplishment will be something more than ornamental.</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-february-19th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-february-19th-1882">Sunday February 19th 1882</h2>
<p>Our usual Sunday. The first step towards active field work was the departure of Lt. Lockwood, Brainard, Frederick and dog team (8) for Beechy. A cold trip it must prove to be.</p>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Pavy and I take a walk to Dutch Island. —see private journal— I find that I have overworked my eyes: have read too much. I must discontinue for a time. It is however difficult to keep from reading during these cold dark days when there is little else to do. I presume I have read at least six hours per day all winter.</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-february-20th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-february-20th-1882">Monday February 20th 1882</h2>
<p>A very cool morning. The light is increasing so that I thought I would try my luck with a shotgun today. Whistler and I started for Watercourse Bay. In the ravine leading to the coal mine we startled up a fine large hare which I followed for miles, succeeded in getting within about 75 yards of him and risked a shot but without effect. The strangest part of the affair was the manner in which the little animal traveled: he stood perfectly upright, kangaroo like, and hopping on his hind legs made enormous strides. Not until he started to ascend the side of the ravine did he assume his proper position of a quadruped.</p>
<p>We passed some time at the grotto mentioned by Mr.&nbsp;Hodson in his interesting article that appeared in the “Frasier’s” after the return of the British expd’n in 1876. It came fully up to our expectations.</p>
<p>On our return we again startled our hare and I persistently followed it by the failing light until it disappeared entirely. It began to snow slightly as we came through the gap and it was difficult to prevent faces from freezing. Whistler’s face was frozen repeatedly and it took some time to remove the frost—J. R. Lt G —see private journal—</p>
<p>My eyes still trouble me.</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-february-21st-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-february-21st-1882">Tuesday February 21st 1882</h2>
<p>I hauled ice as usual. Two of our pups have died. Schneider disconsolate. Weather still keeps very cold. We are making preparations for the celebration of Washington’s Birthday tomorrow. I found my weight still holds good—175 lbs.</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-february-22nd-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-february-22nd-1882">Wednesday February 22nd 1882</h2>
<p>The patriotic Americans among us have some opportunity of expressing loyal sentiments today. Lt. Greely in honor of the day arranged to have it spent as a holiday. An especially palatable dinner was prepared and to diversify the eating exercise we had a shooting match and snow shoe race.</p>
<p>Lt. Greely favored us with a lecture of the “Father of Our Country”. See private journal.</p>
<p>Lt. Lockwood and Brainard return from Beechy. They were engaged in extending the dimensions of the snowhouse there so as to make it accommodate the large parties that will rendezvous there during the spring sledging trips.</p>
<p>The commanding officer called me and I learned some details of the prospective spring work. –see private journal this date.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-02-09/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 00:40:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1882-02-01:1882-02-08</title>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-02-01/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="wednesday-february-1st-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-february-1st-1882">Wednesday February 1st 1882</h2>
<p>Remarkable mock moons observed today. Connell’s birthday. He “does not care to celebrate it.” Says he has not any reason to show any appreciation of the chance of his birth. Lt. G in evening favored us with a few cool remarks on ice. Temp Min -51.0 Max -46.2 , Mean 49.07</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-february-2nd-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-february-2nd-1882">Thursday February 2nd 1882</h2>
<p>I hauled ice as usual. Pup is beginning to work very well in harness. The light has so increased that I could see to read a newspaper out of doors. Temperature still very low.</p>
<p>Min -56.5 Max -45.5., Mean 51.59</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-february-3rd-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-february-3rd-1882">Friday February 3rd 1882</h2>
<p>Nothing noteworthy occurs today. See private diary for account of a circumstance not worth recording here.</p>
<p>Min -62.1 Max 43.3., Mean 48.75</p>
<p>Note without stating it— I wish it understood that_all these figures represent the temperatures observed and corrected.</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-february-4th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-february-4th-1882">Saturday February 4th 1882</h2>
<p>This morning while I was hauling ice with Jens and the dog team the temperature was as low as -60 on the ice floe. This temperature — strange to say—is not difficult to stand for a few hours while exercising violently. Of course it required much care to preserve nose and cheeks from freezing.</p>
<p>Max -43.3 Min -54.6 Mean -47. 85</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-february-5th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-february-5th-1882">Sunday February 5th 1882</h2>
<p>Israel spent two hours in the observatory today. The pursuit of the science of astronomy under the circumstances rather cools the ardor of the youthful observer. Our usual Sabbath occurrences, Rum and Psalms singing in the evening. The observer off duty finds it difficult to sleep. Temp. Max -45.1, Min -54.1, Mean 51.37</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-february-6th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-february-6th-1882">Monday February 6th 1882</h2>
<p>A very cold day. The temperature was below -50 all day. I went to Dutch Island and found the lantern abandoned by Whistler at the time of misadventure after Jens. Temperatures Max -50. Min. -57, Mean 53.65.</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-february-7th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-february-7th-1882">Tuesday February 7th 1882</h2>
<p>Nothing worth recording except the terrible low temperatures. Temperature Max -51.4 Min -58.6., Mean 55.41</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-february-8th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-february-8th-1882">Wednesday February 8th 1882</h2>
<p>Brainard and I walked to Dutch Island. It required great vigilance to prevent our faces from freezing. The cider issued this evening so sour that its use was discontinued by the most of us. Max. 45.5 Min 55.9 Mean 50.99</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-02-01/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 00:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1882-01-21:1882-01-31</title>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-01-21/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="saturday-january-21st-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-january-21st-1882">Saturday January 21st 1882</h2>
<p>Pendulum observations continued. Several fine displays of aurora were seen especially one of curtain formation—color white at some times. It was so bright as to throw shadows from objects on the ice. I attempted to photograph it but did not succeed in getting any impression on the plate. Temp Obs. and Cor. -34.1 to -43.7°F</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-january-22nd-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-january-22nd-1882">Sunday January 22nd 1882</h2>
<p>Our usual Sunday services; day spent in the ordinary way; more sleeping than during the week. Temp. obs. and Corrected -40.7 to -46.1</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-january-23rd-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-january-23rd-1882">Monday January 23rd 1882</h2>
<p>Quite a diversity of phenomena today. A radiant meteor exploded about 7:30 a.m; a lunar halo was observed and a few auroral streaks faintly showed up.</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-january-24th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-january-24th-1882">Tuesday January 24th 1882</h2>
<p>No pendulum observations as the day and night were cloudy. Temp.ramged from -39.2 to 49.3 observed and corrected. “New England rum was so thick at 6 p.m. today that it was a difficult matter to puncture it. Temp -46.4. Lunar halo observed at 6 pm. Biederbeck’s birthday— celebrated in the regulation style. Lt. Lockwood makes some remedies in addition to those he favored us with some time since. As a lecturer he has not improved.</p>
</section>
<section id="jan-26" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="jan-26">Jan 26</h2>
<p>“Deep sea temperatures taken”</p>
</section>
<section id="jan-27" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="jan-27">Jan 27</h2>
<p>“Israel while observing at the astronomical observatory had the misfortune of freezing his foot.”</p>
</section>
<section id="jan-28" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="jan-28">Jan 28</h2>
<p>“Daylight is approaching fast. Two lunar halos were observed during day</p>
</section>
<section id="jan-29" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="jan-29">Jan 29</h2>
<p>“Our usual Sabbath observances in the morning. Lt Kislingbury walked to Cape Murchison and not having informed anyone of his intention caused considerable anxiety by his long absence. A relief party met him near the Station. He reported the tent down at Murchison.”</p>
<p>Two dogs — one eloped with “the queen of one of the other dogs. They came back looking much more for their honeymoon.” This incident “caused some amusement.”</p>
</section>
<section id="jan-30" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="jan-30">Jan 30</h2>
<p>“Bar falling indicating storm. Snow began to fall and continued all day. I walked to Dutch Island with Lt. Kislingbury. I sorted and arranged our library and varnished some negatives. Min -52.7, Max 33.6 Mean -39.12</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-january-31st-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-january-31st-1882">Tuesday January 31st 1882</h2>
<p>Biederbeck looking over the hospital stores found all the hospital brandy frozen solid. One or two bottles had broken. By tasting some of the frozen spirit we were accused of being “hard drinkers”. I hauled some ice with Jens and the dog team. I had considerable amusement from the pups—Askhim’s—antics in the team. We are breaking him in and he does not take kindly to work! But the old (?) dragged him along and he soon found it easier to travel on his legs than on his back. Temp. Obs. and corrected Min. 44.2, Max. -31.1, Mean -38.37.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-01-21/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 00:20:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1882-01-11:1882-01-20</title>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-01-11/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="wednesday-january-11th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-january-11th-1882">Wednesday January 11th 1882</h2>
<p>Weather still continuing cold. Lt. Greely favors us with a lecture on “The Poles” which | did not have the pleasure of hearing as I was assisting Israel at the observatory.</p>
<p>He has so much trouble and difficulty in manipulating the instruments and freezing his fingers that I thought I might save him some of it by sending the signals of time over the telephone for him. I was not of much service however. Israel’s work is very hard in adjusting the transit, he inadvertently froze his nose against the frosty instrument. While we were there the temp stood -45. Temp during day ranged from - 30.8 to 52.9 observed and corrected.</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-january-12th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-january-12th-1882">Thursday January 12th 1882</h2>
<p>Ellison’s birthday. An excellent bill of fare for dinner. Temperature from 31.4 to 36.9 obs. and cor.</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-january-13th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-january-13th-1882">Friday January 13th 1882</h2>
<p>Clear weather. Ther. ranged from -37.0 to -53.2</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-january-14th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-january-14th-1882">Saturday January 14th 1882</h2>
<p>Light snow fell during day. Began falling at 10:40 a.m. Max temp 36.1, min -56.4. Obs &amp; Corrected. No pendulum observations taken on account of the stars being observed.</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-january-15th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-january-15th-1882">Sunday January 15th 1882</h2>
<p>Light snow falling till 6:30 p.m. Maximum temperature -26. Min. 37.1</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-january-16th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-january-16th-1882">Monday January 16th 1882</h2>
<p>Today we experienced the most severe storm I have ever witnessed. Barometer began to fall a little after midnight, 15th, a light breeze setting in from the west at that time. Sky clouded up at this time a small space at the zenith only being partly clear so that a few stars could be seen shining through. Barometer showing more decided fall as the morning advanced. At 8 a.m. slight fall of snow began wind sprang up from SW, blowing 4 miles an hour. The remarkable fall of barometer induced Lt. Greely to have it observed every 15 minutes. About now the expected storm came in full force, Ralston who was on duty found great difficulty in reaching the instrument shelter when the violence of the wind blew out his candle. He returned and Jewell accompanied him. They succeeded in reading the thermometer of -12° 5 a remarkable rise of 17 ° 8 since 7 a.m. Brainard read the tide gauge. By the time 1 o’clock came round the storm had so increased in violence that although several relays and relief parties attempted to reach the instrument shelter none were successful. Connell and] started for the tide gauge but had not struggled through the blinding drift before our lantern was extinguished and we were compelled to return to the Station. I cannot describe the fury of the storm. It was intensely dark, the wind was howling out of the N.E. at the rate of 60 miles an hour carrying with it clouds of frozen snow that cut the face like powdered glass or sparks of fire. The resistance to the body was tremendous, it was impossible to move in an upright position. We lost the path and tumbled over the hill to the ice foot making no attempt to save ourselves. On returning two volunteers joined us and we started again with a red signal lamp. It was Brainard and Biederbeck who accompanied us, their success at 12 o’clock causing them to (?) our attempt. We all stumbled precariously over the bank but could not find the path. We crawled along a short distance when someone behind me said “Let’s try and get back.” Biederbeck’s red light showed up a little in advance however and we followed it and succeeded by mere chance in reaching the snow house over the tide gauge. Our return was not quite so difficult but we had hard work and returned to the quarters bruised and almost frozen. Our faces were covered with a sheet of ice. Observations were now discontinued at the shelter and a thermometer was exposed at the side of our building near the door. At 2:30 p.m. the anemometer cups were blown away. Several tents were blown down and other damage done. The highest velocity recorded before the anemometer blew away was 65 miles but there is not doubt it increased afterwards and we are inclined to think 80 miles per hour not too high an estimate. It was during a lull just before 12 o’clock that the winds shifted around to N.E. where it remained during the remainder of the storm. It ceased to blow with great violence after 4 o’clock but a stiff breeze was felt all day as soon as the observation at the instrument shelter and the tidal gauge resumed. Life lines were placed for the guidance of the observer.</p>
<p>Temp -11° .0 to -31°.1 obs. and corrected</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-jan-17th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-jan-17th-1882">Tuesday Jan 17th 1882</h2>
<p>Snow ended at 3:30 am: clouds cleared away at 6am. Jewell observed the temp of water and thickness of ice today. The working party engaged all day ia repairing the damage of yesterday’s storm. Several tents had to be re-erected: the commissary pile covered up, etc. I again went on duty observing. Temp from -22°.6 to -40.7 obs. and corrected.</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-jan-18th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-jan-18th-1882">Wednesday Jan 18th 1882</h2>
<p>This morning we were smoked out at an early hour by the pipe of our stove choking up. Our heating arrangements are very poor, a good deal of gas is (?) and we breathe much more of it than is compatible with health, especially as we have to spend so much time indoors during the long and cold arctic night. As I note this the sooty comets are falling on me and my surroundings. (see further remarks in private journal)</p>
<p>Temps -31.9 to -47.1</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-january-19th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-january-19th-1882">Thursday January 19th 1882</h2>
<p>The period for monthly magnetic observations has come around and as Israel is still engaged with the pendulum Ralston and Jewell will make the magnetic obs. leaving the regular meteorological work to Henry and I. I find it very tiresome and tedious work—hourly observations, 8 hours on and 8 off. Routine work never suited me.</p>
<p>An auroral arch was observed at 7:35 and strong magnetic disturbances disappeared at 8:30 and another brilliant arch flashed out at 10:30 but disappeared instantly. -34.1 to -43.7 Obs. &amp; Corrected. Gardiner’s 25th birthday. High tide 89 inches.</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-january-20th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-january-20th-1882">Friday January 20th 1882</h2>
<p>Pendulum observations continued. Israe] sticks very faithfully to the work which is very difficult. Some New England rum supposed to be 10 above proof was exposed when I went on duty at midnight and 1 made the following observations regarding the effect of the low temperatures on it. At 2 a.m. a thin coating of slush formed on it—temp -41.7, at 3. slush 1/2 inch in thickness at -44 temp. I again examined it at 5 a.m. and found that it had thickened to the bottom of the vessel resembling somewhat snow saturated with water. Our highest tide was observed today 8 feet 6 inches. The highest observed by the Discovery while here was between 6 and 9 feet. Temp obs. and cor. -31.8 to -47.4 Cross’ birthday.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-01-11/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2024 20:20:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1882-01-01:1882-01-10</title>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-01-01/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="sunday-january-1st-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-january-1st-1882">Sunday January 1st 1882</h2>
<p>This is my first opportunity of setting down the new ’82. Jewell and Lynn started for Mount Campbell the highest point on Bellot Island to read the anemometer and thermometer placed there. After several hours search they returned without finding them.</p>
<p>At 4 p.m. we sat down to our excellent New Years dinner—the turkey. The temperature comparatively warm -21.1 to -29.1. Most of the party enjoyed a siesta during the day as they were somewhat exhausted from watching the Old Year out and New one in.</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-january-2nd-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-january-2nd-1882">Monday January 2nd 1882</h2>
<p>Two mockmoons observed at 1:25 p.m. accompanied with lunar halo and aroral arches. All disappeared at 4 p.m. Temp still warm -21.1 and -26.6 obs. and corrected</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-january-3rd-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-january-3rd-1882">Monday January 3rd 1882</h2>
<p>Brainard and I started for Bellot Island. We were gone five hours. Found the instruments and made the observations. Traveled on snow shoes most of the way. Temp today from -24.6 to -36.2 obs and corrected.</p>
<p>We found them on Mt. Campbell read only -20 showing a warmer strata at that elevation. This was my first walk from Station since my accident.</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-january-4th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-january-4th-1882">Wednesday January 4th 1882</h2>
<p>The arrangements for taking pendulum observations are now all complete. Israel is awaiting clear weather so that astronomical observations for time can be taken. Hourly watches to continue through twenty four hours announced today. The true time is recorded at which the tide rises or falls an inch. Lt. Lockwood lectures in the evening on “Sledging.” His remarks were principally quotations from the accounts of former arctic explorers and must have cost him considerable labor and research. Temp -25.5 to -33.6. I did not state result of anemometer reading on Bellot Island by myself and B. Velocity of wind since Dec 1st 4,210 miles.</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-january-5th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-january-5th-1882">Thursday January 5th 1882</h2>
<p>Tide gauge observations continued. Two mockmoons were observed. Temp. -26.8 to 37.6 obs. and corrected.</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-january-6th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-january-6th-1882">Friday January 6th 1882</h2>
<p>Israel commenced surveying the pendulum today assisted by Connell who ran the chronograph for him. Temp -34.1 to 42.2 obs. And cor.</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-january-7th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-january-7th-1882">Saturday January 7th 1882</h2>
<p>Pendulum observations continued. Temp -28.2 to -33.6. Obs. And Cor.</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-january-8th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-january-8th-1882">Sunday January 8th 1882</h2>
<p>Our usual Sabbath. Bible reading by Lt. G. in the moming; the remainder of the day very quiet until 7 p.m. when the ration of rum is issued after which conversation flows fast and furious. This New England rum of ours appears to contain more volubility and eloquence to the square yard than any stimulant hitherto administered. An argument can be readily started on any topic on Sunday evening. Temp observed and corrected -28.2 to -49.2.</p>
<p>The sun light at noon is gradually growing brighter. Lt. Kislingbury could read the time indicated by his watch by it today.</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-january-9th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-january-9th-1882">Monday January 9th 1882</h2>
<p>Today experienced the coldest temperature yet observed by us. The ther. ranged from -44.0 to -56.4 obs. and corrected.</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-january-10th-1882" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-january-10th-1882">Tuesday January 10th 1882</h2>
<p>A still lower temperature from -47.2 to -57.2. obs. And corrected. Israel in taking signal observations at astronomical observatory, froze his toe.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1882/1882-01-01/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2024 20:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1881-12-19:1881-12-31</title>
  <dc:creator>George W Rice</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-12-19/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="monday-dec-19th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-dec-19th-1881">Monday Dec 19th 1881</h2>
<p>Began reading new tide gauge, and Gardiner up for first time today.</p>
<p>The heavens were filled with auroral displays all day too numerous and varied to describe, but some appearances very beautiful. Ther. from -41.2 to -49.7. Obs and corrected.</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-dec-20th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-dec-20th-1881">Tuesday Dec 20th 1881</h2>
<p>Two meteors were observed falling today, one of them exhibiting a beautiful rosy colour. A faint aurora was also seen.-40.2 to -46.7° F was the range of standard thermometer observed and corrected.</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-dec-21st-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-dec-21st-1881">Wednesday Dec 21st 1881</h2>
<p>My shoulder is very painful. I think it is much more seriously injured than appears in examination which can only be superficial. Today is Brainard’s birthday and his bill of fare furnishes us with a splendid table for dinner. Deep sea temp. taken by Henry. Standard thermometer read from -40 to -46.7 today observed and corrected, correction is -3.8</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-dec-22-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-dec-22-1881">Thursday Dec 22, 1881</h2>
<p>Weather much warmer, light snow began to fall at 11 a.m. Temp ranged from -26.6 to -28.8. obs and cor. Many jokes were made about the warm weather. One or two of the party seriously observing that the day was uncomfortably sultry.</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-dec-23-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-dec-23-1881">Friday Dec 23, 1881</h2>
<p>Snow continues. Weather still warm -23.3 —28.1 Cross is going around with a badly swollen cheek the effect of toothache.</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-dec-24th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-dec-24th-1881">Saturday Dec 24th 1881</h2>
<p>Salor’s birthday, occurring today was celebrated by the usual gastronomical preparations for an extra dinner. Snow ceased falling at 3 p.m. It being Xmas eve the presents kindly sent by some thoughtful parties in the States were distributed by our commander amid much chaffing and sport. The kindness of the donors was highly appreciated. The interest attending the opening of the mysterious packages was very great. I found myself the possessor of a pipe accompanied by a neat chamois skin bag filled with fine tobacco. I have no way of (?) the use of the articles however and find the (?) to me, property something of an elephant.</p>
<p>A handsome lap-robe intended for Ryan who returned on the “Proteus”, was raffled for and although I came within one of winning Ellison was the happy man. Egg nog was passed around and drunk to the health of loved ones at home but we were compelled to admit that the same exhilarating beverage imbibed by our friends was superior to ours. The eggs which were preserved and rather mummy-fied. We have managed to arrange a programme for Monday night which will require but little preparation. Temp. obs and cor -33.6</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-december-25th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-december-25th-1881">Sunday December 25th 1881</h2>
<p>Light snow fell part of the day. Weather cloudy remainder. A very quite Christmas. Lt Greely read a chapter from the Scripture as usual on Sundays. Our dinner was the main feature of the day. A copy of the bill of Fare can be seen on a page previous to this. Considerable sleeping indulged in as we all feel rather fatigued after last nights dancing. In the evening an extra quantity of the (?) in the form of New England rum was issued the exhilarating effect of which added to the pleasure of looking over the fine illustrations in some London Graphics of a late date enabled us to pass a very enjoyable evening. It was impossible however to prevent our minds from wandering over snow and ice to the homes of friends and loved ones so vividly brought before us by the season of Christmastide. We think there was not one of our small party who did not indulge in a retrospective view of the events and surroundings of our last Xmas. Ther. Obs and cor. Ranged from -24 to 39.9.</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-december-26th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-december-26th-1881">Monday, December 26th 1881</h2>
<p>Temperature stationary. -22.6 to -26.6, obs. And cor. After midnight last night all hands being up and no disposition of retiring appearing a dance was proposed. It met with such favor and was kept up till morning. Schneider and his violin furnishing the music. I was unable to assist him as usual owing to the state of my arm. There was much hilarity and no sleep secured, so after breakfast everything became quiet, nothing occurring to break the silence but the regular snoring of one of the sleepers. In the evening our entertainment came off a programme of which will be here inserted.</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-dec-27-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-dec-27-1881">Tuesday Dec 27, 1881</h2>
<p>Sea temperature observed today. Surface 29.1 and at a depth of 33 feet 28.8 Thermometer obs. And cor., Max. 27.1, min. 37.4</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-december-28th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-december-28th-1881">Wednesday, December 28th 1881</h2>
<p>Weather clear. Temp. from 32.1 to 44.2</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-december-29th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-december-29th-1881">Thursday, December 29th 1881</h2>
<p>Lt. Greely lectures on “war memories” — an interesting narrative of some of his personal experiences at Fredericksburg. Thermometer ranged from -36.1 to 45.2 obs &amp; cor.</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-dec-30th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-dec-30th-1881">Friday Dec 30th 1881</h2>
<p>“Nothing noteworthy” -32.4 to 46.7 was the range of temperature.</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-dec-31st-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-dec-31st-1881">Saturday Dec 31st 1881</h2>
<p>A cool but pleasant day. The evening was given over to Bacchus and Terpsichore. I removed my arm from the bandages and attempted to relieve Schneider in furnishing music for the dancers but found the positions of holding the violin a painful one for my shoulder. Temperature from -34.1 to -46.2</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{w_rice2024,
  author = {W Rice, George},
  title = {1881-12-19:1881-12-31},
  date = {2024-06-16},
  url = {https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-12-19/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-w_rice2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
W Rice, George. 2024. <span>“1881-12-19:1881-12-31.”</span> June 16,
2024. <a href="https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-12-19/">https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-12-19/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-12-19/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2024 20:10:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1881-12-10:1881-12-18</title>
  <dc:creator>George W Rice</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-12-10/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="saturday-dec-10th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-dec-10th-1881">Saturday Dec 10th 1881</h2>
<p>Lt. snow during the afternoon. Lt Greely issued an order for all hands to return at 11 p.m. as he considers it demoralizing to sleep at all times as we do now, as there is no difference in the appearance of night and day.</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-dec-11th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-dec-11th-1881">Sunday Dec 11th 1881</h2>
<p>Our usual Sabbath, differing very little from the other days of the week. Lt. Greely read the passage which is usually read at the opening of Congress this being the day on which the event occurs. In the evening several of the cavalrymen gave a very amusing imitation of the Indian war dance as they have seen it on the Frontier. The falling of a remarkably bright was observed at 6:30 p.m. accompanied by a very loud report. Auroral displays were seen at intervals during the day; at some times in the form of streamers and at others in a curtain formation. They were of remarkable brilliance. At 2:30. we observed the brightest arch that has been seen since our arrival.</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-dec-12th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-dec-12th-1881">Monday Dec 12th 1881</h2>
<p>Cloudy weather. Light fall of snow. Party working on an ice wall to break the cold draught at the corner of our quarters. I hauled a few loads of ice as usual.</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-dec-13th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-dec-13th-1881">Tuesday Dec 13th 1881</h2>
<p>Today Jens the Esquimaux concluded he would vary the monotony of our life by absconding. His elopement was discovered at breakfast time. He had been seen in the early morning however and we naturally concluded that he had not traveled far. After breakfast Lt. Greely instructed Brainard and I to start from a point outside the Station and by walking in opposite directions discovered (Jens) tracks leading from the Station.</p>
<p>It was about 8:30 a.m. when we started. Henry volunteered to go with me and Whistler went with Brainard. It was very dark, the sky overcast and no moon in the heavens. Fortunately for Jens light snow had fallen the day previous so that his tracks could be easily found and distinguished from others. I soon found his tracks following the beaten track towards Dutch Island. We communicated with Brainard and Whistler who soon found us and we proceeded at a rapid rate expecting to overtake the fugitive in a short time as the track looked fresh and we knew that he had been very long on the road. After proceeding a short distance we thought it best to send back word to the Station to follow us with a dog team in case Jens should lead us a long chase. Henry and Frederick the other Esquimaux returned.</p>
<p>Brainard Whistler and I followed the trail expecting to catch up to Jens at any moment for we could see unaided by any lights he had not been able to follow the path directly but wavered on and off. With our lanterns we moved on very rapidly until Dutch Island distant two miles was reached. Beyond that point the path is not well defined as it has not been traveled since the last party came in from Cape Beechy. We saw that our game had turned off at right angles towards the ice foot so as to follow the coastline and avoid being lost in the ice. His track now became difficult to follow much time being lost in keeping (?) of them. When about five miles from the home we were joined by Dr.&nbsp;Pavy with Frederick and dog team. We kept on at the most rapid rate practicable, two of us going in advance with the lantern, the others following the track as we found it. The ice foot was very rough and the darkness was so intense that it was impossible to select the most favorable route for the sledge even if the erratic course taken by Jens allowed for it. When near Distant Cape the progress was very slow and at one place I dropped behind to allow the Dr.&nbsp;a better position behind the sledge. We had been walking behind it intending to join him as soon as the point was passed. I had just left the advance and being able to hold on to the standards of the sledge and depend upon it for guidance. I blew out the candle in my lantern to economize our light. As soon as I dropped behind, the sledge disappeared in the dark and in groping my way after it I met with several severe falls. I did not go far before I slipped and was thrown violently against a projecting piece of ice. It was several minutes before I could move from my prone position on the ice, when I discovered that my shoulder was undoubtedly broken. I regained my footing and appreciating the importance of catching up with the sledge, I lit my candle under great difficulty presented by the wind and the use of one hand only. I started at the best gait I could suffering intensely and encountered several more falls in one of which my light went out and delayed me. I expected the sledge to wait for me at the moment they discovered my absence. It appeared they were so interested in the chase that my absence was not noticed or they thought I was following at my leisure. I plotted along my candle burnt out. I overtook the party at a point a little south of Cape Murchison distant about ten miles to reach while our (treacherous) way traveled much farther. They had just concluded to wait for me. On learning (of) my condition Whistler started to return with me.</p>
<p>Brainard and the Dr.&nbsp;continuing in the way intending to go as far as Cape Beechy and spending the night at the snowhouse if they did not find Jens. Whistler and I made but slow progress on the return as 1 was compelled to avoid jarring my shoulder. When near Distant Cape Whistler began to complain of the cold, a few moments after he began to talk incoherently and before a mere halfway to Dutch Island he was delirious. My position was becoming rather unpleasant. Whistler overcome by the cold, was entirely unresponsive and it took all my will and ingenuity to induce him to walk. He was continually falling down and could hardly resist the temptation to remain on the ice. I attempted to lead him and having no light our footing was so uncertain that I was continually jarred by missteps which caused me to suffer intensely from my shoulder. I had to cajole, coax and command Whistler at every step to get him along. I began to fear for his life: had he refused to move he might have died in a very few moments.</p>
<p>We got as far as Dutch Island when Dr.&nbsp;Pavy, Brainard and the Esquimaux overtook us with the dog sledge. I at once gave the Dr.&nbsp;the state of affairs and told him it was necessary to get Whistler to the Station as soon as possible. It was necessary to make him run behind the sledge and we learned on reaching the Station that when near the Station they had to place him on the sledge as he had lost all use of his limbs.</p>
<p>Brainard and I reached the Station at 4 p.m.</p>
<p>We had been out about 8 hours, traveled at least twenty miles with the temperature at -30 on one of the darkest days of the winter. Whistler was delirious for several hours, his nose and cheeks frozen but otherwise he suffered no bad consequences. Dr.&nbsp;examined my shoulder and found fracture not complete but the bone evidently cracked and ligature injured. Jens was overtaken a short distance beyond the point from which we started to return. He came back quite penitently but did not attempt to explain the cause of his strange conduct. Light snow was falling almost all day.</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-dec-14th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-dec-14th-1881">Wednesday Dec 14th 1881</h2>
<p>A few days ago Lt. Greely requested me to try and arrange some sort of entertainment as a diversion for the party the time hanging heavily on our hands at present. I found it impossible to carry out any such plan successfully as our party is so small that after making a cast of performers there would be but a small audience remaining. Then it would be impossible to rehearse or arrange anything except in the presence of the others so by the time of the performance the programme would be stale and uninteresting. I therefore gave up the idea but suggested to the men that we should invite Lt. Greely to lecture before us. They were pleased with the suggestions and I made our wishes known to Lt. Greely. He kindly assisted and tonight favored us with some interesting remarks on the Polar question: a subject absorbing to us at present. An Aurora observed at 8p.m.</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-dec-15th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-dec-15th-1881">Thursday Dec 15th 1881</h2>
<p>The party are exercising by banking up magnetic observatory. My shoulder is very painful; sleep is almost an impossibility. Frederick the other Esquimaux has exhibited the desire to follow the example of Jens. In a melodramatic manner he flourished a huge wooden cross in one hand and with the other on his heart bade us all “good bye” intimating that he was tired of life and about to immolate himself on the Shrine of the Polar Question. We dissuaded him however. Temperature Max -27.4° F Min -46.2° F</p>
<p>( Copy of Christmas dinner menu)</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-dec-16th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-dec-16th-1881">Friday Dec 16th 1881</h2>
<p>Deep sea temperature observed at norm today. Surface 28.9, at depth 33 ft. -28.7 Thermometer observed and (?) -38.4 — -46.5</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-dec-17th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-dec-17th-1881">Saturday Dec 17th 1881</h2>
<p>The party are exercising by banking up the magnetic observatory. An Aural streamer observed. Range of the observed and corrected from -38.2 to 46.2</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-dec-18th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-dec-18th-1881">Sunday Dec 18th 1881</h2>
<p>Israel commenced taking magnetic observations the usual monthly lasting three days , today. Usual Bible reading in the morning. Ther. Obs. And Cor. Ranged from -40.2 to 46.7</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{w_rice2024,
  author = {W Rice, George},
  title = {1881-12-10:1881-12-18},
  date = {2024-06-16},
  url = {https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-12-10/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-w_rice2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
W Rice, George. 2024. <span>“1881-12-10:1881-12-18.”</span> June 16,
2024. <a href="https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-12-10/">https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-12-10/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-12-10/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2024 20:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1881-12-01:1881-12-09</title>
  <dc:creator>George W Rice</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-12-01/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="thursday-december-1st-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-december-1st-1881">Thursday December 1st 1881</h2>
<p>I took up the duty of making the hourly observations again at midnight. The most difficult part of the tour is that leading to the tidal gauge. We are compelled to descend the steep bank to the ice foot and notwithstanding the quantity of ashes sprinkled in the path it is slippery and unsafe. I’ve had several severe falls, the heavy cork sole shoes adding to the uncertainty of the footing. Ralston has demolished several of Bender’s tin candle lanterns by falling on them. We have accused him of tobogganing on them after the style of the Montreal club. The weather is becoming warmer.</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-dec-2nd-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-dec-2nd-1881">Friday Dec 2nd 1881</h2>
<p>Temperature increasing. Weather fair. I did not state that Sgts. Ralston and Brainard visited Mt. Campbell on Bellot Island for the purpose of reading the anemometer and thermometer placed there permanently. The anemometer has registered 657 miles since it was first placed in position on Oct 9th. Thermometer showed minimum temp since Oct 31st to have been -38°0. Temperature of water and thickness of ice in harbor: temp air -27, surface of water -29.1 Depth of 33 ft. 29°.2 Thickness of ice 33” Snow began falling at 11:35 a.m. ending at 5:30 p.m</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-dec-3rd-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-dec-3rd-1881">Saturday Dec 3rd 1881</h2>
<p>Weather clear except a short time at midday. Jewell is on duty again. Gardiner is getting along very nice and hauled ice in morning. Frederick the Eskimo has for some time appeared disheartened and has been making me the confidant of his gloomy prospects, such as that of running away. Some days since Jens acted in the same manner but we reassured them of their safety and security. They have both been treated with the greatest kindness by all the party but as there has been little for them to do for some time past they have become lonesome and homesick and doubtless imagine all manner of things. As Frederick appeared to be very much in earnest today I sat up at night to intercept any attempt on his part to escape.</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-dec-4th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-dec-4th-1881">Sunday Dec 4th 1881</h2>
<p>Two beautiful mock moons at midnight which lasted until 8 a.m. They exhibited the prismatic colors. At 4 a.m. contact arches were formed. The mock moons were about 22° from the real. An almost complete circle surrounded the moon passing through the mock moons.(diagram)</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-dec-5th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-dec-5th-1881">Monday Dec 5th 1881</h2>
<p>Weather cold. Front put in the icehouse over pendulum. I exercised myself, dogs and Jens in hauling ice.</p>
<p>A beautiful Lunar halo with mock moons was observed at 6 p.m.</p>
<p>The most interesting occurrence of the day was the lunar eclipse of the moon which commenced about 10 a.m. and lasted for over an hour. It was almost a total eclipse and the moon during the time exhibited different colors. An auroral streamer was observed. (diagram)</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-dec-6th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-dec-6th-1881">Tuesday Dec 6th 1881</h2>
<p>Weather clear. I exercised by hauling ice as usual. Some members of the party still engaged in the pendulum building.</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-dec-7th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-dec-7th-1881">Wednesday Dec 7th 1881</h2>
<p>Nothing of importance occurred to vary the monotony of our everyday or night life. The usual exercise taken by the party is walking, hauling ice, working in the pendulum shelter. This work lasts for an hour or two each day. The hauling of ice falls to me and I shall be loath to give it up as it furnishes me with healthful exercise much more exhilarating and beneficial than mere walking on account of the activity required in following the sledge and assisting the Esquimaux in managing the dogs. Weather fair. Lunar halo observed.</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-dec-8th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-dec-8th-1881">Thursday Dec 8th 1881</h2>
<p>Weather clear. Biederbeck went to Distant Cape for Hudson Bay sledge left there by Jewell some time since. Nothing noteworthy occurred.</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-dec-9th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-dec-9th-1881">Friday Dec 9th 1881</h2>
<p>Weather fair. Sky clear. Pendulum building completed today.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{w_rice2024,
  author = {W Rice, George},
  title = {1881-12-01:1881-12-09},
  date = {2024-06-15},
  url = {https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-12-01/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-w_rice2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
W Rice, George. 2024. <span>“1881-12-01:1881-12-09.”</span> June 15,
2024. <a href="https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-12-01/">https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-12-01/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-12-01/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 20:40:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1881-11-15:1881-11-22</title>
  <dc:creator>George W Rice</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-15/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="tuesday-november-15th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-november-15th-1881">Tuesday November 15th 1881</h2>
<p>The weather’s still cold. Several acids and oils were placed in the instrument shelter to determine the relative freezing point. They all became much denser in a short time. Coal oil assumed the consistency of syrup.</p>
<p>Light snow 3:45 p.m. to 11 p.m.</p>
<p>“Lt. Greely today issued order No 9 to the effect that Thursday Nov 24 will be set apart as a day of Thanksgiving corresponding with the day observed as a holiday in the United States. It is proposed that we shall make it a holiday and engage in races rifle matches and other amusements. The commanding officer offers prizes to contestants in the different matches.</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-nov-16th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-nov-16th-1881">Wednesday Nov 16th, 1881</h2>
<p>The moon left us today. Lt. Greely and two men engaged on the pendulum piers. Others hauling work —-in addition to the usual routine of outdoor work. Lt Lockwood, Henry and I have decided to start a paper which is to be called the “Arctic Moon” and will appear bi-monthly. We issued a prospectus today informing the party of our intentions and soliciting contributions and subscribers.</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-november-17-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-november-17-1881">Thursday November 17, 1881</h2>
<p>I hauled some ice this morning, although the moon has disappeared there is significant light to work by. Lt. Lockwood with two men was engaged in finishing the ice house in the harbor which was commenced some time ago. It is proposed to use it as a shelter for a self-registering tide gauge.</p>
<p>In laying the foundation of pendulum piers the temperature of the earth at a depth of 18 inches was found to be 7°.0, the temp of air — 5.0. This is in the shed or lean-to adjoining officers quarters.</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-november-18th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-november-18th-1881">Friday November 18th 1881</h2>
<p>The programme for Thanksgiving was arranged today. The amusements will consist of a snow-shoe race, foot race, shooting race, and most interesting of all, a dog race between two teams in harness to sledges. Jens and Frederick the Esquimaux will be the drivers. A grand dinner will be prepared.</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-nov-19th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-nov-19th-1881">Saturday Nov 19th, 1881</h2>
<p>It was decided to have a thorough cleaning out of the quarters today. As the building was inhabited while the work was going on I took a walk to Dutch Island with Lt. Kislingbury. When we returned everything looked much brighter, cleaner and more cheerful. The weather continues clear and comparatively, not very cold.”</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-november-20th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-november-20th-1881">Sunday November 20th, 1881</h2>
<p>Lt. Greely read to us a chapter from the Bible as usual and which, most of us took a constitutional walk. In the evening Schneider’s violin and I furnished instrumental music as an accompaniment to the vocalists engaged in rendering some ancient hymns and songs. Weather clear.</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-november-21st-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-november-21st-1881">Monday November 21st, 1881</h2>
<p>A clear day. Lt. Lockwood completed his ice house. The race course was prepared by removing snow and placing stakes. The course is on the ice in harbor, near the shore. The distance for snowshoe race will be 200 yards and return; foot race 100 yards straight away. The sledge race will be from Station to Dutch Island, a distance of two miles, and return.</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-november-22-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-november-22-1881">Tuesday November 22, 1881</h2>
<p>Lt. Lockwood, Henry and I were busy preparing our paper for press. It is to be issued on Thursday. It appears that we shall have to depend on ourselves for original matter as no contributors to our columns have made themselves known.</p>
<p>House was banked with snow at some exposed parts. Weather clear. A very brilliant meteor fell at 10:30 p.m. from Zenith to horizon. No tail. Color blue.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{w_rice2024,
  author = {W Rice, George},
  title = {1881-11-15:1881-11-22},
  date = {2024-06-12},
  url = {https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-15/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-w_rice2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
W Rice, George. 2024. <span>“1881-11-15:1881-11-22.”</span> June 12,
2024. <a href="https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-15/">https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-15/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <category>newspaper</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-15/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 01:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1881-11-23:1881-11-30</title>
  <dc:creator>George W Rice</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-23/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="wednesday-november-23rd-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-november-23rd-1881">Wednesday November 23rd 1881</h2>
<p>Brainard and Cross were experimented this morning on the feasibility of lighting a short rifle range artificially for the use of the marksmen in the coming Thanksgiving. They found that at 25 yds good light could be thrown on a target and also sufficient for sighting the gun.</p>
<p>The pendulum piers are now sufficiently high; and the erection of an ice house over them was commenced today. Weather clear, an aurora was observed at 9 a.m. It disappeared in short time; was of ribbon formation.The cooks are making great preparations for tomorrow’s dinner with the exception of the regulation turkey the menu is of the real Thanksgiving flavor.</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-november-24th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-november-24th-1881">Thursday, November 24th 1881</h2>
<p>The day clear and favorable for the sports to be engaged in. Of course the drawbacks of darkness and cold must be taken into consideration. We are unfortunately in the dark period of the moon the presence of which would supply us with all the light we would require. Thermometer over 60 below the freezing point making this doubtless the coldest Thanksgiving day that has ever been celebrated.</p>
<p>At an early hour the men were all engaged in perfecting their arrangements for the different races; the cooks preparing their (hands?) and even the dogs making noisy demonstrations as if to show that they too entered into the spirit of the day.</p>
<p>After breakfast the first thing on the programme was the snowshoe race. It was called for 10 am: but for an hour before that time the clattering of the shoes could be heard through the quarters as the men tested the security of the fastenings. We all repaired to the course on the ice in harbor which was staked out and very imperfectly lighted. The distance was 200 yds and return. Eight competitors entered and a good start was effected. And now the affair became most amusing to the bystanders. Many of the men were not familiar with the cumbersome footgear and this added to the difficulty of finding the way over the ill light course, made their progress most awkward and erratic. The “Montreal Snowshoe Club” would have considered it a strange exhibition. An unperceived piece of ice would trip some luckless fellow up and away he would go floundering in the snow to serve as a footmat for his impetuous rivals who were following him with more haste than speed.</p>
<p>As soon as the unfortunate could recover his 2 x 4 feet he would probably be run into by some fleet footed Mercury who could not distinguish him from the surrounding snow in which he had been wallowing. Many were the mishaps before the goal was reached.</p>
<p>Sgts. Brainard, Ralston, Gardiner came in and won the first three prizes. They reached the home stake in the order in which they are named.</p>
<p>Prizes were: 1st Bot of pres. Peaches: 1 gill rum, (towel) and soap. 2nd 1 gill rum, towel and soap</p>
<p>We then repaired to the quarters where bets were settled and paid and other wagers laid on the result of the approaching running race. I found myself the winner of a large amount of tobacco (our legal tender) having backed Brainard against Gardiner, who was the favorite.</p>
<p>I acted as stakeholder for the party and in that capacity handed over a large amount of tobacco to the lucky gamblers.</p>
<p>The running race footrace now came up and after a tie between three of the six contestants it was soon over and the first place won by Ellis, Henry second and Linn third. Prizes; 1st 1 pt.&nbsp;rum, towel and soap, 2nd 1 gill rum and towel, 3rd 1/2 gill and soap.</p>
<p>The rifle shooting came last and most of the party engaged in it. Henry won the first prize (bot of pres. peaches, 1/2 pt rum and soap), Jens 2nd (1 gill rum, towel and soap) and Cross 3rd 1/2 gill rum and soap. (over) We were much interested in the result of the dog driving match between the two Esquimaux. They were made to understand it perfectly i.e.&nbsp;the arrangement, and set about harnessing up the dogs. While they were doing so we went inside the quarters expecting to be notified when they were in readiness so that we might see and regulate the start. However the canine Jehus took the matter in their own hands. We discovered they had gone and patiently awaited their return. They came in shortly at a terrific pace Frederick ahead thus winning the pipe and half pound of tobacco constituting the prize.</p>
<p>Three auroral streamers were observed.</p>
<p>We were now ready for dinner which was served at 4 o’clock. I give here the bill of fare which considering our distance from market was varied and palatable.</p>
<p>Our chef de cuisine excelled himself:</p>
<p>(Oyster soup, crabs, lobster salad, Eider Ducks, boiled ham, green corn, lima beans, asparagus, jelly cake, fruit and sponge cakes, Peach pie, blueberry pie, vanilla ice cream, coffee, warm biscuit, nuts figs etc.) After dinner grog was issued larger quantity than usual and songs were in order.</p>
<p>Lt. Greely having appointed me distributor of the prizes I attached the said role of each of the party and succeeded in getting up a most ridiculous dress suit for the occasion: an old long tailed coat of Jewell’s was transformed by the use of shears into a swallow tail of remarkable pattern, a dilapidated white vest, immense collar, profuse jewelry manufactured by the tinsmith, and an immense pair of Esquimaux boots completed the costume. Lt. Greely made us a short address after which I conferred the prizes.</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-november-25th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-november-25th-1881">Friday November 25th 1881</h2>
<p>In chronicling our celebration of yesterday I lost sight of the fact that the first number of our paper was issued yesterday. It made a very good appearance and we the editors, thought it interesting. It was little appreciated however, by the majority of the party. Henry’s department was the personal column and some of his lists although perfectly harmless gave great offense to those who were alluded to. The bully Whistler as usual made a complete ass of himself. Frederick also considered himself greatly aggrieved. Although contributions had been solicited there was no response except from Lt. Greely who sent in a short letter over “Occasional.” For my part of the sheet see “Arctic Moon” of date Nov 24” editorial Arctic Moon account of Lt. K’s kindness to dogs Wrangle Bay trip, (?) from the Esquimaux, etc. Lt. Lockwood furnished the preamble and heroic account of and adventure of Lt. Kislingbury and Dr Pavy.</p>
<p>An Auroral arch was observed at 6:45 and other at 9:55 a.m. The latter was the most beautiful, exceedingly bright and of a delicate pale yellow color. Weather clear. Temperature low.</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-november-26th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-november-26th-1881">Saturday, November 26th 1881</h2>
<p>Weather clear. An observation of the temperature of the sea was taken today with the following result. Temp at surface 28°0. Thickness of ice 29”</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-november-27th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-november-27th-1881">Sunday November 27th 1881</h2>
<p>Temperature low. Cross while taking a walk had his ear frozen. Lt. Kislingbury and I walked to Dutch Island as a constitutional. Notwithstanding the exercise of great care on my part I froze one of my cheeks.</p>
<p>At 10 a.m. an auroral streamer was seen.</p>
<p>The laugh is decided against Sgt.&nbsp;Brainard today. He started with two or three companions to walk to Dutch Island, which by the way, is the objective point of all pedestrians, the intervening path being well beaten, and was not aware that the two Eskimos had preceded him. It is very dark now and they had proceeded but half way when by the dim light they saw what they supposed to be a pack of ravenous wolves emerging from the ice hummocks and making for them. They were unarmed but Brainard with great coolness told his companions to get their knives in readiness and prepared to repel the onslaught of the ferocious beasts. Hastily opening their knives some of them insignificant pen knives they stood in an agony of suspense until the near approach of the animals proved them to be dogs that had accompanied the Eskimos and had started on in advance to meet the new party with demonstrations of delight and no belligerent intention whatever.</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-nov-28th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-nov-28th-1881">Monday Nov 28th, 1881</h2>
<p>Several appearances of auroral light were observed today. Temperature low. I hauled six loads of ice with the Eskimos and dog team. This furnished me with an amount of exercise which is beneficial, but arduous. I find the dogs more interesting than one would suppose. They exhibit remarkable sagacity and intelligence. Nothing, however, can overcome their propensities for fighting. During the couple of hours I was engaged with them I noticed nine different encounters which were usually general, no non-combatants to be seen.</p>
<p>They have divided into two parties and it does not appear possible to associate one party with the other. I was only using one team and the other apparently jealous of the preference shown the first barred the road at every point where it was possible and contended the passage of the loaded sledge. I was compelled to precede the team and drive them off. Lunar halo and mock moons were seen at 3:30 p.m. They presented a beautiful appearance.</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-nov-29th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-nov-29th-1881">Tuesday Nov 29th 1881</h2>
<p>I hauled ice as usual in the morning. Jewell being ill I took the observations from 4 p.m. until midnight. New aurora observed. Weather clear all day- lowest temp observed -37.5° F.</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-november-30th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-november-30th-1881">Wednesday November 30th, 1881</h2>
<p>During the day the temperature fell to -43°. The Mercury froze at -37°.9. While taking the 3 p.m. observation Gardiner while on his way to the tidal gauge fell and fractured his leg above the ankle. I finished his tour and will take his place at midnight. Being desirous of completing my knowledge of German and Biederbeck wishing to improve his English we have made an arrangement by which we shall interchange instructions in our mother tongues. We had our first lesson this evening.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{w_rice2024,
  author = {W Rice, George},
  title = {1881-11-23:1881-11-30},
  date = {2024-06-12},
  url = {https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-23/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-w_rice2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
W Rice, George. 2024. <span>“1881-11-23:1881-11-30.”</span> June 12,
2024. <a href="https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-23/">https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-23/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <category>thanksgiving</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-23/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 01:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1881-11-08:1881-11-14</title>
  <dc:creator>George W Rice</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-14/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="wednesday-november-8-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-november-8-1881">Wednesday November 8, 1881</h2>
<p>I forgot to state in yesterday’s entry that on our way back we found “Gypsy” safe and sound. She had increased her progeny to triplets. We wrapped them all in deer skin and brought them in on the sledge. After arriving at Beechy and while we were feeding the dogs, one of the pups fell out and before we noticed it, became partly frozen and afterwards died. Spent comfortable night and started for home 12 a.m. Shortly after we started it began to snow and the track along the icefoot was difficult to follow. In crossing St.&nbsp;Patrick’s Bay we lost the track. Lt. Kislingbury and the Dr.&nbsp;considered us as going too far into the Strait, while I contended that we were already too far up the bay. We found ourselves among hummocks and I left the sledge and proceeded ahead. I persisted in keeping out in the mouth of the bay and at last found the old track. We arrived at home station at 7 p.m. Learned that Lt. Lockwood and party had only arrived a few hours earlier. They found it impossible to cross the Strait on account of the moving ice in channel and also the soft slushy ice that would neither bear a foot passenger or allow boat to pass was another impediment. They started for home from Beechy on the 7th when near the entrance of St.&nbsp;Patrick’s Bay they found the icefoot overflowed with the exceptionally high tide they had that day. Most of the party got their feet wet and wanted to go into camp at once. Lt. L. however advised keeping on till Cape Murchison was reached. As soon as they could examine their feet several found them badly frozen. Biederbeck was dragged in on the sledge and will probably loose his great toe.</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-nov-9th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-nov-9th-1881">Wednesday, Nov 9th, 1881</h2>
<p>I have concluded to omit the entry of the daily temperatures until the comparative readings now being made will furnish us with a correction for the thermometers. At present the readings are considered slightly incorrect by Lt. Greely. I will afterwards enter them as —–notes. Today the weather is clearing, with falling temperatures. No aurora was observed.</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-november-10th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-november-10th-1881">Thursday November 10th, 1881</h2>
<p>The parties are engaged for a short time each day in outdoor work. Some remove the ice forming on the tide gauge; others bank up the house etc. I spent about an hour each day in hauling ice with Jens and a team of dogs. The ice is for conversion into water for daily use. An aurora was observed early this morning, also a faint streamer in the evening. A lunar halo of 22° was seen at 6 p.m.</p>
<p>Considerable excitement over two fires that occurred today. The first was insignificant occurring in the lean to while Saler was filling lamps. The one caught fire but was smothered before any damage done. About 4 p.m. Ellison was in the carpenter tent and attempted the experiment of filling a gasoline lamp without extinguishing it. He made a very successful failure, but will not likely again try it. In an instant he was enveloped in flames the whole can of fluid igniting. He rushed out shouting “Fire!” Our two Babcock extinguishers were brought into (?) and after a short time the fire was subdued but not before some more tools and clothing was destroyed. Ellison was badly burned.</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-november-11-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-november-11-1881">Friday November 11, 1881</h2>
<p>Ellison was badly burned. His face and hands are excoriated so that they appear raw. He presents a sorry appearance. Weather is fair. I hauled four loads of ice and will continue to do so until the moon leaves us as after that the light will not be sufficient. Two mock moons were observed from 9:45 to midnight. Weather is growing colder.</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-november-12th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-november-12th-1881">Saturday November 12th, 1881</h2>
<p>Today we experienced the lowest temp so far. Weather clear during the day, but cloudy at night. It did not affect us very unpleasantly (the cold) and our outdoor avocations were carried on as usual.</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-november-13th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-november-13th-1881">Sunday November 13th, 1881</h2>
<p>Our usual Sabbath varying the routine of the week by its accompanying divine service in morning and issue of grog at night. The day generally spent in reading and sleeping. In the evening some hymns and old songs were sung with a strong chorus. Weather continues to keep fine and clear. Two mock moons appeared at 10:30 p.m. and passed away at midnight. No auroras were observed.</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-november-14th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-november-14th-1881">Monday November 14th 1881</h2>
<p>Lt. Greely commenced work on the pendulum piers in the lean-to today. Gardiner and Connell assisted him. They succeeded in getting a good foundation laid using quick plaster of Paris and cement. With the Eskimo and dogs I have hauled my quota of ice; the tide gauge measured the ice formed in the pool at the (?). Auroral streamers now observed at noon and continued at intervals during the afternoon and evening. Sgt.&nbsp;Israel was engaged in taking magnetic observations which continue for three days during each month.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{w_rice2024,
  author = {W Rice, George},
  title = {1881-11-08:1881-11-14},
  date = {2024-06-10},
  url = {https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-14/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-w_rice2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
W Rice, George. 2024. <span>“1881-11-08:1881-11-14.”</span> June 10,
2024. <a href="https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-14/">https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-14/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <category>expeditions</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-14/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2024 02:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1881-11-01:1881-11-07</title>
  <dc:creator>George W Rice</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-07/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="tuesday-nov-1-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-nov-1-1881">Tuesday, Nov 1, 1881</h2>
<p>Remarkable deposit of hoar frost noticed by the observers. Sufficient was collected in gages to measure .05 of an inch. This measurement however includes all that has fallen since last snowstorm but most of it fell this morning. I assisted Israel in ascertaining the deep sea temperature.</p>
<p>Preparations going on all day for the attempt to cross over the Strait to Polaris Harbor and “Halls Rest.” The men are exhibiting considerable ingenuity in fitting themselves out. Our supply of clothing and paraphernalia for field work in this climate is sadly deficient of much that is necessary. For foot gear especially we are badly off. The cork soled arctics are much to heavy to walk in, Esquimaux boots we have next to none and those few we have too small. There are not enough of the buckskin moccasins to go around. I have not received a pair as they were issued while I was out in the field. Dr.&nbsp;Pavy generally fits me out from his private store of Esquimaux boots which is extensive.</p>
<p>By evening Lt. Lockwood and his party of seven men completed their preparations packed their sledges with the provisions etc and pulled it out to Distant Cape so as to allow a start in the morning free of the sledge encumbrance…</p>
<p>They returned at 5 p.m. An unusual dinner was prepared by order of Lt. Greely in honor, I presume, of Lt. L’s departure on his hazardous attempt.</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-nov-2nd-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-nov-2nd-1881">Wednesday Nov 2nd 1881</h2>
<p>Lt. Lockwood and party started this morning for Cape Beechy from which point they propose to pass over to Polaris Bay. The load on sledge, an English one formed here, weighed 1,100 — a heavy drag through the snow and over the icefoot.</p>
<p>I followed at 9:30 with dog sledge and Jens the Esquimaux. The plan is that I am to support Lt. Lockwood, aiding him with the dog team until the arrival of Dr. Pavy when I join him for a trip to Wrangle Bay to carry rations for the spring trip. My team was composed of but 7 dogs as two of the bitches had newly born litters and not the same number of serviceable dogs, 7, were left for the Dr.&nbsp;The load of 600 lbs that we had on the sled was therefore too heavy. I met with the Dr.&nbsp;and Lt. Kislingbury near Dutch Island and arranged with him to leave one bag of bread at Murchisons to be brought on by his team as he expected to have a light load. Overtook the party of Lt. Lockwood at Murchison at 2 p.m. They were plodding along steadily and expected to reach Beechy by night. I furnished them with a drink of chocolate I had brought warm in our sleeping bag and proceeding on advance. I reached Cape Beechy at 7 p.m. and Lt. L and party at 8 p.m. We occupied the snowhouse erected some time ago and were very comfortable I brought but one sleeping bag as it reduced the weight on the sled and Jens the Eskimo and I occupied it.</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-november-3rd-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-november-3rd-1881">Thursday November 3rd, 1881</h2>
<p>Slept comfortably last night. Jens and I filled the sleeping bag so that the warmth of our bodies was confined and kept us warm. Temperatures during the night -17.</p>
<p>Lt. Lockwood started out with Jens and the dogs for Cape Murchison to bring two bags of coal. He also intended to examine the small boat left in St.&nbsp;Patrick’s Bay by the English in 1875. I, assisted by Ellis, put out rations and built a snow pedestal for a telescope we had brought. Brainard with rest of party started back for remainder of their load abandoned the night before. Brainard and party returns at 1:30 p.m. Lt. K returns at 4 p.m. He forgot to bring sack of pemmican which was to be part of his load. Mock moons observed at 8 p.m. Temperature -11.</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-november-4-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-november-4-1881">Friday November 4, 1881</h2>
<p>Lt. Lockwood sent me for the boat at St.&nbsp;Patrick’s Bay. Started with dogs and sledge. Returned with boat at 3 p.m. During my absence Lt. L and party made attempt to cross the Straits. They took whale boat which made their load so cumbersome that it was impossible to advance over the rough ice. They consequently returned after a few hours. Lt. L proposes making another attempt with the smaller boat brought from St.&nbsp;P Bay. Dr.&nbsp;Pavy and Lt. K arrived at snowhouse at 6 p.m. They made but slow progress being 12 hours from home station. Dr.&nbsp;is on his way to Wrangle Bay with more rations to be used in the spring campaign. I shall accompany him with the other dog team.</p>
</section>
<section id="november-5th-188" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="november-5th-188">November 5th 188]</h2>
<p>I observed an amusing tableau last night before retiring. The snow house not being large enough to accommodate us all, Ellis Saler and Biederbeck pitched a tent outside and occupied a sleeping bag large enough to hold three men. Ellis and Saler retired and left the candle burning for Biederbeck who was making preparations for cooking breakfast in the morning. I happen to look in the tent and was almost convulsed with laughter to see “Old Mate”, one of the most disagreeable and mangy looking of all the dogs, occupying the middle place in the sleeping bag left vacant for B. He was lying on his side head on the pillow with one paw thrown lovingly over Ellis’ neck. As I laughed he looked up and expression said as plainly as I can interpret it: “It is all right. I am one of them.” At 9:30 Dr.&nbsp;Pavy and I started for Wrangle Bay. Lt. Kislingbury accompanied him with one sledge and team and Jens and I had the other one.</p>
<p>When we left Lt. Lockwood and party were making preparations for crossing the Strait. They are repairing the boat I had brought from Murchison</p>
<p>We proceeded for a short distance when Jens told me that the little bitch “Gypsy” exhibited symptoms of matemity. He tried to drive her back thinking she would return to the snow house but she returned to the team. We then proceeded with her. She soon became tired an ill and we carried her on the sledge. This reduced our teams to six dogs each as three bitches were left at the home station with litters. We had a difficult time traveling over much ground which was also icy. Camped at 7:15 p.m. in the valley.</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-november-6th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-november-6th-1881">Sunday November 6th 1881</h2>
<p>During the night Gypsy managed to enter the tent and while we were at breakfast gave birth to two pups. After breakfast Jens and I built a small snow house and placed the mother with the pups in it. I left some pemmican so that she would not starve during our absence. We then broke camp and deserted her. 9:30 am. We traveled all day and had a most interesting journey. We found the traveling very good. At about noon we entered the lower ravine leading in a more easterly direction towards Wrangle Bay.</p>
<p>(Drs’ sled) was on a much lower level than the one we were on and we made a most exciting descent into it. Finding our efforts to hold the sledge back to no avail I threw myself on the sledge. Jens dragged by the standards behind. The dogs started on the full run and would not be controlled; the sledge however descended faster than they and running away some rocks the lines became entangled and the sledge stopped. Found good traveling in the lower valley and reached our destination Wrangle Bay at 2:30 p.m. It was then beginning to snow.</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-november-7-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-november-7-1881">Monday November 7 1881</h2>
<p>Added our load of rations to the depot already established and started to return at 1:30 p.m. and after a successful trip arrived at Snowhouse at 10 p.m. Learned by a note left by Lt. Lockwood that he had returned home having failed.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{w_rice2024,
  author = {W Rice, George},
  title = {1881-11-01:1881-11-07},
  date = {2024-06-10},
  url = {https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-07/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-w_rice2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
W Rice, George. 2024. <span>“1881-11-01:1881-11-07.”</span> June 10,
2024. <a href="https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-07/">https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-07/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <category>expeditions</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-11-07/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2024 01:50:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1881-10-14:1881-10-31</title>
  <dc:creator>George W Rice</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-10-14/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="friday-october-14-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-october-14-1881">Friday October 14, 1881</h2>
<p>Weather fair, a Solar halo was observed between 10 a.m. and 11:30 a.m. The sun has condescended to shine for such a short time each day for a long time. Today Lt. Greely somewhat startled us by announcing that today was the last on which we would see the sun ’till at least the 29th of February. We all rushed out door and sure enough Old Sol only exhibited himself for a few moments and then set in a glorious glow of colors. The refraction of its rays presented a beautiful effect in the horizon for some time after. Ther. ranged from maximum -10 to minimum -27.4.</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-october-15-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-october-15-1881">Saturday October 15, 1881</h2>
<p>Weather fair. Two mock moons —–appeared at 5:30 p.m. and disappeared at ll p.m. They displayed vertical rays of light. Temp. from -10 to -27.4</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-october-16-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-october-16-1881">Sunday, October 16, 1881</h2>
<p>Weather fair. “Deep sea temperature (taken every fifth day) was again taken today. Nineteen and one half new inches of new ice had formed since the last hole was cut in ice. An aurora observed at 7 p.m. lasting about 20 minutes. It was perfectly white. Very low temperature (Max -18 Min -32)</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-october-17-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-october-17-1881">Monday October 17, 1881</h2>
<p>Cloudy weather, cleared up at 3 p.m. Temp. Max.-10 Min. -29</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-october-18-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-october-18-1881">Tuesday October 18, 1881</h2>
<p>Clear weather. Sergeant Linn, Connell and Henry started for the coal mine a Watercourse Bay to get out coals. They returned at 3 p.m. They found no difficulty in tumbling down several tons of coals. On their way over to the mine they found the ice cavern or grotto mentioned in Sir Geo Nares’ work. (Max -11 Min -33.9) Cool</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-october-19-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-october-19-1881">Wednesday October 19, 1881</h2>
<p>Weather clear, partly cloudy during latter part of day. I started with Jens the Eskimo and a team of nine dogs to take a load from the mine to Cape Murchison a pleasant dog drive. I arrived home at 3:45. Getting quite dark at that time. At 9 p.m. an aurora was observed. Several meteors seen, the most remarkable by Israel at 9 pm. Ther. From -16 to -29</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-october-26th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-october-26th-1881">Thursday October 26th, 1881</h2>
<p>The darkness is increasing rapidly. We are compelled to use artificial light almost all the twenty four in the quarters. Jupiter plainly visible at 2:30 p.m. Connell took coal from Watercourse Bay to Cape Murchison. Weather warm. -2 to -23</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-october-21st-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-october-21st-1881">Friday October 21st, 1881</h2>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Pavy left station at 9:30 a.m. for the coal mine, returning at 2:30 p.m. with 430 lb coal. Jupiter, Arctivas Capella , and Alpha Gemminium were plainly seen at mid day. A new experience to see stars plainly shining at noon. (Max +4 Min -15)</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-october-22-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-october-22-1881">Saturday October 22, 1881</h2>
<p>Sun ended at 12:30 a.m. Following stars visible at 1 p.m.; Marc Polans, Vega, Capelle, Castor, Prelix, and Cygni. Jupiter and Arcturus are now visible during the twenty four hours. An aurora was observed; the magnometer during the display was —-disturbed. Temperature from (+7 -20)</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-oct-23-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-oct-23-1881">Sunday Oct 23, 1881</h2>
<p>Lockwood accompanied by Sgt.&nbsp;Brainard, and Pvt. Connell started for Cape Beechy. They took Eskimo Frederick and one dog team. They are to build snowhouse at Cape Beechy for the accommodation of the sledging parties in the spring. Ther. Maximum +7 to Minimum -20.</p>
<p>Usual Sunday services as follows; reading the Bible and prayer for the absent and singing sacred and otherwise during the evening.</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-october-24th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-october-24th-1881">Monday October 24th, 1881</h2>
<p>Another load of coals from Watercourse Bay to Murchison Sgt Gardiner. Temp from -2 to -15.9</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-oct-25th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-oct-25th-1881">Tuesday Oct 25th, 1881</h2>
<p>At 9:30 a Solar halo appeared —above the horizon, color pink. This halo as determined by it’s position and altitude was 23° above the sun. Maximum +7. Minimum -10.</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-oct-26th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-oct-26th-1881">Wednesday Oct 26th, 1881</h2>
<p>Pvt. Ellis made another coal trip. Lt. Lockwood and party return from Cape Beechy at 4:10 p.m. They succeeded in building a snow house which by two nights’ occupation proved to be comfortable. The weather continues comparatively warm today from +8 to -10 was the temperature.</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-oct-27th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-oct-27th-1881">Thursday Oct 27th, 1881</h2>
<p>We were busy for an hour or two building an ice wall around the house. We have been furnished with a few hours exercise every morning in constructing this wall which will afford a shelter from the north wind. I have the honor of being appointed Superintendent of Construction. The temperature still continues mild. Maximum +2° F to Minimum -12° F</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-oct-28th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-oct-28th-1881">Friday Oct 28th, 1881</h2>
<p>Added another tier to the ice wall. Snyder and Biederbeck while taking a constitutional walk in the evening were somewhat startled by hearing a wolf howling. It was so dark they could not see him but distinctly heard his footsteps in the snow. They were about a mile from the station but did not tarry. I’m prepared to certify that O’Leary’s best time was beaten. Thermometer, Max. +5, Minimum -10.</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-oct-29-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-oct-29-1881">Saturday Oct 29, 1881</h2>
<p>It is now getting quite dark during the day at midday. Polaris was Plainly visible. Several displays of aurora were observed in the evening.</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-oct-30th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-oct-30th-1881">Sunday Oct 30th, 1881</h2>
<p>It is now fourteen days since the sun disappeared below the horizon and to test the power of active rays still existing in the faint light reflected from sun at noon I propose to attempt another photograph. Israel, Whistler started after breakfast and took the direction of Distant Cape. We hauled photographic apparatus on Hudson Bay Sledges.</p>
<p>I exposed dry-plate for about one hour about noon. Sun must have been 6° or 8° below horizon. Amused ourselves while plate was exposed—target practice with rifle Whistler had brought along. Our Sunday evenings are generally spent in singing. Lt. Kislingbury, Gardiner, Ellis &amp; Schneider taking prominent parts. Their repertior (sic) consists of old songs and older hymns. I sometimes assist with the violin.</p>
<p>Usual quart of ram dispensed. Said rum is not a particularly delectable article of spirits tasting more like diluted commercial alcohol than anything else. For the first month or more we used the English rum deposited by the Nares expedition at Cape Hawkes and appropriated by us. Our own ‘New England’ is a poor substitute.</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-oct-31st-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-oct-31st-1881">Monday Oct 31st, 1881</h2>
<p>Weather clear. Sgt.&nbsp;Ralston &amp; Pvt. Henry made a trip to the summit of Bellot I. to read Max and Min thermometers. Max recorded since Sept 30 21.05 Min -33.8 All hands making preparations for an attempt to cross the Straits under Lt. Lockwood.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{w_rice2024,
  author = {W Rice, George},
  title = {1881-10-14:1881-10-31},
  date = {2024-05-19},
  url = {https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-10-14/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-w_rice2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
W Rice, George. 2024. <span>“1881-10-14:1881-10-31.”</span> May 19,
2024. <a href="https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-10-14/">https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-10-14/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <category>camp</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-10-14/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>1881-10-06:1881-10-13</title>
  <dc:creator>George W Rice</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-10-06/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="thursday-october-6-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-october-6-1881">Thursday October 6, 1881</h2>
<p>Our chief object in visiting the Bellows was to have the muskox meat left by the party in Sept.&nbsp;from the place the cattle had been killed to the icefoot that it might be convenient for a party to take home to camp.</p>
<p>Arose at 6:30 a.m. Cooked breakfast over our alcohol lamp. Minimum temperature recorded -24 during night.</p>
<p>Started for a load of the meat, found it about 2 miles from the shore, and brought down one carcass, a difficult matter to drag the sledge with such a load as the stones were not covered by the snow.</p>
<p>It was very uncomfortable as a strong breeze was blowing causing us to suffer much from the cold. It required the utmost vigilance to prevent our faces and hands from freezing. Brainard had his nose frostbitten several times and despite my caution I had my cheeks frozen. By 4 p.m. we had hauled four loads of the meat to the shore. We then went to the tent and prepared a hasty meal, and at 4:30 started again for another load. At 4 the thermometer read -18 and at 4:20 when we left the tent it registered -20.</p>
<p>Returned at 7p.m. tired out and cold. The thermometer showed us the temperature had fallen to -25° F.</p>
</section>
<section id="friday-october-7th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="friday-october-7th-1881">Friday October 7th, 1881</h2>
<p>After another uncomfortable night we got up early to bring the last remaining carcass of meat down. Temperature during night -25. Started for home station at 10:40 a.m. Arrived home at 5 p.m. It was then very dark and snowing steadily.”</p>
<p>A footnote “I made one exposure for negatives at “Bellows”.</p>
</section>
<section id="saturday-october-8th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saturday-october-8th-1881">Saturday October 8th, 1881</h2>
<p>Snow falling from 3:30 a.m. ’till 6:10 p.m., The thickness of the ice measured near tide gauge. Result of 5 ft. 7inches. Two mock moons were observed. Temperature +6 to -6.</p>
</section>
<section id="sunday-october-9-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sunday-october-9-1881">Sunday, October 9, 1881</h2>
<p>Light snow falling most of the day. Dr.&nbsp;Pavy and Whistler return from their attempt to reach Cape Joseph Henry at 4:30 p.m. they were unable to reach it owing to the straights being still open and no ice foot on which to travel near Lincoln Bay.</p>
<p>Temperature ranged from +1 to -16. Sunday services and rum as usual.</p>
</section>
<section id="monday-october-10-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="monday-october-10-1881">Monday October 10, 1881</h2>
<p>Weather very thick during day. Snowed from 5 p.m. to 9 p.m. Lt Lockwood and Sgt.&nbsp;Jewell started to walk to Cape Baird at 8 a.m. Their object is to determine if sledging to that point is practicable. They return at 8:40 p.m. We had become anxious about them as it had become very dark. A party with lanterns met them about 3 miles from camp. Thermometer, Maximum -1, minimum -11.9.</p>
</section>
<section id="tuesday-october-11-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuesday-october-11-1881">Tuesday October 11, 1881</h2>
<p>Israel took deep sea temperature today. Sgt Linn with the two Eskimos and dog teams started for the “Bellows” to bring back a load of meat. Temperature, Maximun -2 to minimum -19.</p>
</section>
<section id="wednesday-october-12th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wednesday-october-12th-1881">Wednesday October 12th 1881</h2>
<p>Lt. Lockwood started this morming with three men for the purpose of establishing a depot at Cape Baird. Linn returned at noon with 927 pounds of muskox meat from the Bellows. A Solar halo (mock suns) was observed close to the horizon at 11a.m.</p>
<p>Very low temperature today, the thermometer reads from -8 to -25.9 —rather cool for Indian summer.</p>
</section>
<section id="thursday-october-13th-1881" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thursday-october-13th-1881">Thursday October 13th, 1881</h2>
<p>“Brainard and I started for Mt. Ovibus, distant to base six miles. We rode part of the way with Linn who was on his way to the Bellows after more meat. Mt. Ovibus is estimated to be 2600 ft high. Our object was to reach the summit and examine with the telescope the valley leading from Muskox Bay to see if it offered a practical route to United States range of mountains. We were three hours in making the ascent from base at some places the climbing was most difficult and found a heavy deposit of snow at the top of the mountain. We were forced to use our snowshoes which we fortunately carried. It was my first attempt at walking with such foot gear, and I found I could travel comfortably. We did not accomplish anything as the atmosphere was hazy and could see no distance. Reached home at 5:30 p.m.</p>
<p>Lockwood and party returned at 7:45p.m. Linn got back at noon with the remainder of the Musk Ox meat from the Bellows.</p>
<p>Weather fair- low temperature</p>
<p>Maximum -11.</p>
<p>Minimum -27.4</p>
<p>The above thermometer readings are for the 24 hours froml2 midnight to 12 midnight. The same now applies to all the temperatures I have herein recorded.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-reuse"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{w_rice2024,
  author = {W Rice, George},
  title = {1881-10-06:1881-10-13},
  date = {2024-05-05},
  url = {https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-10-06/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-w_rice2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
W Rice, George. 2024. <span>“1881-10-06:1881-10-13.”</span> May 5, 2024.
<a href="https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-10-06/">https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-10-06/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>diary</category>
  <category>rice</category>
  <category>camp</category>
  <guid>https://rmflight.github.io/george_rice_polar_expedition/Diary_Entries/1881/1881-10-06/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
